<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Joseph Thurman - Thesis</title><link href="http://www.josephthurman.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.josephthurman.com/feeds/thesis.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.josephthurman.com/</id><updated>2018-10-01T17:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>The Cross Product</title><link href="http://www.josephthurman.com/crossproduct.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-10-01T17:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-10-01T17:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Joseph Thurman</name></author><id>tag:www.josephthurman.com,2018-10-01:/crossproduct.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We're nearly ready to give the geometric interpretation of quaternionic multiplication that we've been working toward ever since we &lt;a href="http://www.josephthurman.com/quaternions2.html"&gt;first defined the quaternions&lt;/a&gt;. Instead of considering the four-dimensional quaternions, we've spent the last &lt;a href="http://www.josephthurman.com/vectorsinR3.html"&gt;few&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.josephthurman.com/dotproduct.html"&gt;posts&lt;/a&gt; considering three-dimensional vectors, specifically discussing a product operation called the &lt;a href="http://www.josephthurman.com/dotproduct.html"&gt;dot product&lt;/a&gt; that we can …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We're nearly ready to give the geometric interpretation of quaternionic multiplication that we've been working toward ever since we &lt;a href="http://www.josephthurman.com/quaternions2.html"&gt;first defined the quaternions&lt;/a&gt;. Instead of considering the four-dimensional quaternions, we've spent the last &lt;a href="http://www.josephthurman.com/vectorsinR3.html"&gt;few&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.josephthurman.com/dotproduct.html"&gt;posts&lt;/a&gt; considering three-dimensional vectors, specifically discussing a product operation called the &lt;a href="http://www.josephthurman.com/dotproduct.html"&gt;dot product&lt;/a&gt; that we can use to understand geometry in three dimensions.  In this post, we'll introduce a second product operation in three dimensions, the so-called &lt;em&gt;cross product&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Intuition for the Cross Product&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cross product is an operation that takes in two three-dimensional vectors and returns a three dimensional vector. (Recall that the dot product, in contrast, takes in two vectors and returns a number.) In order to see how this operation works, notice that if we're given two arbitrary vectors in &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{R}^3\)&lt;/span&gt;, then chances are these two vectors will determine a two-dimensional plane in &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{R}^3\)&lt;/span&gt;. For a simple example, the two vectors &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{e}_1 = (1,0,0)\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{e}_2 = (0,1,0)\)&lt;/span&gt; that point in the &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(x\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(y\)&lt;/span&gt; directions in our standard picture determine the &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(xy\)&lt;/span&gt;-plane, the set of all points with &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z\)&lt;/span&gt; coordinate equal to &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(0\)&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Two Vectors Determine a Plane" src="http://www.josephthurman.com/planefromvectors1.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Two vectors determine a plane&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One way to visualize the plane created by two vectors is to see that if we add two vectors using &lt;a href="http://www.josephthurman.com/vectorsinR3.html"&gt;the parallelogram method&lt;/a&gt;, then the parallelogram enclosed by the vectors can be extended to the plane determined by the two vectors.  We can use this to visualize the plane determined by the vectors &lt;span class="math"&gt;\((1,2,3)\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\((0,-2,-1)\)&lt;/span&gt;, shown in red and blue, respectively, in the picture below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Parallelogram method to visualize the plane determined by two vectors" src="http://www.josephthurman.com/planefromvectors2.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Parallelogram method to visualize the plane determined by two vectors&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Considering the parallelogram rule for addition is also helpful for understanding the conditions for which two different vectors don't actually determine a unique plane. This occurs when the two given vectors don't make a parallelogram under vector addition because they point either in the same direction or in exactly opposite directions.  As we see illustrated below, in this case there are many possible planes that contain both vectors, instead of just one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Multiple planes containing by vectors in opposite directions" src="http://www.josephthurman.com/planefromvectors3.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Multiple planes containing by vectors in opposite directions&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example in the picture above the two vectors &lt;span class="math"&gt;\((2,0,0)\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\((-3,0,0)\)&lt;/span&gt;, which point in opposite directions, can both be contained in many different planes, including the &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(xy\)&lt;/span&gt;-plane and the &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(xz\)&lt;/span&gt;-plane, consisting of points that have &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(y\)&lt;/span&gt;-coordinate equal to zero.  We can also produce many other planes containing these vectors by rotation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore we have that, given two vectors in &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{R}^3\)&lt;/span&gt;, we can usually use them to define a plane.  The observation that leads to the cross product is to note that there is a second way to describe a plane in &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{R}^3\)&lt;/span&gt;, using a &lt;em&gt;normal vector&lt;/em&gt;.  A vector is said to be a &lt;em&gt;normal&lt;/em&gt; to a plane if that vector is orthogonal (perpendicular) to any vector that sits in the plane. Conversely, given a vector, we can produce a plane by considering all of the vectors orthogonal to the given one.  These two processes are illustrated below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Describing a plane by a normal vector" src="http://www.josephthurman.com/normalvector1.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Describing a plane by a normal vector&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the picture above, we see that the plane is determined by the blue vector &lt;span class="math"&gt;\((1,0,0)\)&lt;/span&gt; and the red vector &lt;span class="math"&gt;\((0,2,-1)\)&lt;/span&gt;.  This plane can also be described by considering a normal vector, shown in black.  This vector is the vector &lt;span class="math"&gt;\((0,1,2)\)&lt;/span&gt;, and it's not hard to see that any vector that lies in the plane will be perpendicular to this vector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus we have a method to take two vectors and produce a plane, and then to take a plane and produce a normal vector.  Putting these two processes together, we obtain the cross product.  That is, the cross product is the operation that takes in two vectors and returns a vector that is normal to the plane determined by those two vectors.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a slight problem with this definition: given a plane, there is not a unique normal vector to that plane.  This is illustrated below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Normal vectors are not unique" src="http://www.josephthurman.com/normalvector2.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Normal vectors are not unique&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the same plane as above, and the black vector is also the same. We can see, though, that it is not the only vector normal to the plane - the blue vector, which points in the same direction as the black vector, is also normal, as is the red vector, which points in the exact opposite direction.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of being determined by a single normal vector, a plane is determined by a single normal line.  We can then pick many different normal vectors by choosing a direction and a length along that line.  Therefore in order to fully define the cross product we need to decide on a systematic way to assign a length and a direction to the normal vector that we pick.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We'll consider length first. Given vectors &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{v}, \mathbf{w}\)&lt;/span&gt;, we choose the length of the cross product vector, which is written as &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{v} \times \mathbf{w}\)&lt;/span&gt;, by saying that
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
\| \mathbf{v} \times \mathbf{w} \| = \| \mathbf{v} \| \, \| \mathbf{w} \| \sin \theta
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
where &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\theta\)&lt;/span&gt; is the angle between the vectors &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{v}\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{w}\)&lt;/span&gt;.  Recall that all of these lengths and angles can be measured by using the &lt;a href="http://www.josephthurman.com/dotproduct.html"&gt;dot product&lt;/a&gt; operation defined in the previous post.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why do we make this choice? Recall from above that we can consider the plane defined by the vectors &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{v}\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{w}\)&lt;/span&gt; as extending the area inside the parallelogram associated to those two vector via vector addition.  The number &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\| \mathbf{v} \| \, \| \mathbf{w} \| \sin \theta\)&lt;/span&gt; is then exactly the area of this parallelogram.  Another important point is to notice that in the case that the vectors &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{v}\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{w}\)&lt;/span&gt; are on the same line, and therefore don't define a unique plane, then the angle between them is either &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\theta = 0^\circ\)&lt;/span&gt; or &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\theta = 180^\circ\)&lt;/span&gt;, and in either case we have &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\sin 0^\circ = \sin 180^\circ = 0\)&lt;/span&gt;.  Therefore the cross product of two vectors that don't actually determine a unique plane is the zero vector &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{0} = (0,0,0)\)&lt;/span&gt;.  Note that this means that the cross product is not a multiplication operation - we can take two non-zero vectors and their cross product can be the zero vector.  This means, following the general discussion from a few &lt;a href="http://www.josephthurman.com/vectorsinR3.html"&gt;posts back&lt;/a&gt;, that there is no way to define a "division" operation that is inverse to the cross product operation.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's still one issue remaining in defining the cross product.  We've seen how to get the length of the cross product vector, but still can't be certain of the direction.  For a simple example, we can return to the situation of the vectors &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{e}_1 = (1,0,0)\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{e}_2 = (0,1,0)\)&lt;/span&gt;.  As we said above, the plane associated to these vectors is the &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(xy\)&lt;/span&gt;-plane, and we see that any vector of the form &lt;span class="math"&gt;\((0,0,z)\)&lt;/span&gt; will be normal to this plane.  Using the formula for lengths described above, we therefore have that &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{e}_1 \times \mathbf{e}_2\)&lt;/span&gt; should be either &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{e}_3 = (0,0,1)\)&lt;/span&gt; or &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(-\mathbf{e}_3 = (0,0,-1)\)&lt;/span&gt;, as these are the two unit vectors that point in the &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z\)&lt;/span&gt; direction.  But which one should it be?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can choose either one, and the standard choice is to choose &lt;span class="math"&gt;\((0,0,1)\)&lt;/span&gt;, so that &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{e}_1 \times \mathbf{e_2} = \mathbf{e}_3\)&lt;/span&gt;.  This choice can be remembered using the &lt;em&gt;right-hand rule&lt;/em&gt; for the cross product. To find the direction of the cross-product &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{v} \times \mathbf{w}\)&lt;/span&gt;, you can begin by pointing the fingers of your right hand in the direction of the vector &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{v}\)&lt;/span&gt;, then curling your fingers toward the vector &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{w}\)&lt;/span&gt;, as if making a fist.  If you extend your thumb while making this motion, then it points in the direction of the cross product vector &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{v} \times \mathbf{w}\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Right hand rule" src="http://www.josephthurman.com/righthandrule.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Right hand rule&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is shown in the picture above.  If you begin with the fingers of your right hand pointing out of the page in the direction of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{e}_1 = (1,0,0)\)&lt;/span&gt;, which is shown in red in the above picture, and then curl them to &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{e}_2 = (0,1,0)\)&lt;/span&gt;, which is shown in blue, then your hand will curl and rotate in the direction of the black arrow, and your thumb will point upward, in the direction of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{e}_3 = (0,0,1)\)&lt;/span&gt;, shown in green.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that this choice is totally arbitrary - we could just as well have chosen to define &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{e}_1 \times \mathbf{e}_2 = (0,0,-1)\)&lt;/span&gt;, which would correspond to the &lt;em&gt;left-hand rule&lt;/em&gt; for determining the direction of the cross product.   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fact that we have to make this choice means that the order of the elements of the cross product matters. This can be verified by example - if you use the right-hand rule to determine the direction of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{e}_2 \times \mathbf{e}_1\)&lt;/span&gt;, you'll notice that your thumb points down instead of up, that is, &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{e}_2 \times \mathbf{e}_1 = (0,0,-1) = -\mathbf{e}_3\)&lt;/span&gt;.  This means that the cross product is &lt;em&gt;not commutative&lt;/em&gt; - in general, &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{v} \times \mathbf{w}\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{w} \times \mathbf{v}\)&lt;/span&gt; are not the same vector.  In fact, it's not hard to see that &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{v} \times \mathbf{w} = - \mathbf{w} \times \mathbf{v}\)&lt;/span&gt;, that is, changing the order of the cross product changes the direction of the resulting vector. For this reason, we say that the cross product is &lt;em&gt;anti-commutative&lt;/em&gt; - it commutes, but with a minus sign. You might remember that &lt;a href="http://www.josephthurman.com/quaternions2.html"&gt;quaternionic multiplication&lt;/a&gt; is also not commutative - we'll return to this point in the next post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Formula for the Cross Product&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To summarize, the cross product is a procedure that takes in two vectors &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{v}\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{w}\)&lt;/span&gt;, and returns a third vector. If &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{v}\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{w}\)&lt;/span&gt; together determine a plane, then this third vector is perpendicular to that plane, with length and direction determined by the choices above.  If &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{v}\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{w}\)&lt;/span&gt; do not determine a unique plane, the cross product is just the zero vector &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{0} = (0,0,0)\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understanding the above geometric interpretation of the cross product is the most important part of this post, but it isn't useful for actual computations.  In order to compute, we need the following formula. If &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{v} = (v_1, v_2, v_3)\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{w} = (w_1, w_2, w_3)\)&lt;/span&gt; are two vectors, then their cross product is given by the formula
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
\mathbf{v} \times \mathbf{w} = (v_2 w_3 - v_3 w_2, -v_1 w_3 + v_3 w_1, v_1 w_2 - v_2 w_1 )
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's check that this is the correct formula. First, the above formula does define an anti-commutative operation - if you exchange all of the &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(v\)&lt;/span&gt;'s and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(w\)&lt;/span&gt;'s in the above formula, you'll get the same vector, but multiplied by &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(-1\)&lt;/span&gt; in each entry. Next, we observe that the formula above follows the right-hand rule - we can easily check that &lt;span class="math"&gt;\((1,0,0) \times (0,1,0) = (0,0,1)\)&lt;/span&gt;, that is, &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{e}_1 \times \mathbf{e}_2 = \mathbf{e}_3\)&lt;/span&gt;, using this formula.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a third check, we can observe that the vectors &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{v}\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{v} \times \mathbf{w}\)&lt;/span&gt; are orthogonal. The dot product of these two vectors is zero, since
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{align*}
\mathbf{v} \cdot (\mathbf{v} \times \mathbf{w}) &amp;amp;= (v_1, v_2, v_3) \times (v_2 w_3 - v_3 w_2, -v_1 w_3 + v_3 w_1, v_1 w_2 - v_2 w_1 ) \\
  &amp;amp;= v_1 (v_2 w_3 - v_3 w_2) + v_2(-v_1 w_3 + v_3 w_1) + v_3(v_1 w_2 - v_2 w_1) \\
  &amp;amp;= 0
\end{align*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Anticommutativity then gives that &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{w}\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{v} \times \mathbf{w}\)&lt;/span&gt; are also orthogonal. In order to be sure this formula is correct, it remains to show that the vector &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{v} \times \mathbf{w}\)&lt;/span&gt; that it defines has the proper length.  We'll skip that check here, but the interested reader could try to prove that for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Next Time - Finally Understanding the Quaternions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We now have both a geometric intuition and a number-crunching formula for the cross product, and with this understanding we're finally ready to consider quaternionic multiplication from a geometric point of view.  In the next post, we'll see that quaternionic multiplication gives a way to combine the dot product and cross product into a single operation. Using this, we'll be able to understand quaternionic multiplication in terms of rotations and distances in three dimensions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;if (!document.getElementById('mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#')) {
    var align = "center",
        indent = "0em",
        linebreak = "false";

    if (false) {
        align = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "left" : align;
        indent = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "0em" : indent;
        linebreak = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? 'true' : linebreak;
    }

    var mathjaxscript = document.createElement('script');
    mathjaxscript.id = 'mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#';
    mathjaxscript.type = 'text/javascript';
    mathjaxscript.src = 'https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.0/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML';
    mathjaxscript[(window.opera ? "innerHTML" : "text")] =
        "MathJax.Hub.Config({" +
        "    config: ['MMLorHTML.js']," +
        "    TeX: { extensions: ['AMSmath.js','AMSsymbols.js','noErrors.js','noUndefined.js'], equationNumbers: { autoNumber: 'AMS' } }," +
        "    jax: ['input/TeX','input/MathML','output/HTML-CSS']," +
        "    extensions: ['tex2jax.js','mml2jax.js','MathMenu.js','MathZoom.js']," +
        "    displayAlign: '"+ align +"'," +
        "    displayIndent: '"+ indent +"'," +
        "    showMathMenu: true," +
        "    messageStyle: 'normal'," +
        "    tex2jax: { " +
        "        inlineMath: [ ['\\\\(','\\\\)'] ], " +
        "        displayMath: [ ['$$','$$'] ]," +
        "        processEscapes: true," +
        "        preview: 'TeX'," +
        "    }, " +
        "    'HTML-CSS': { " +
        "        styles: { '.MathJax_Display, .MathJax .mo, .MathJax .mi, .MathJax .mn': {color: 'inherit ! important'} }," +
        "        linebreaks: { automatic: "+ linebreak +", width: '90% container' }," +
        "    }, " +
        "}); " +
        "if ('default' !== 'default') {" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('HTML-CSS Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax['HTML-CSS'].FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('SVG Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax.SVG.FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
        "}";
    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(mathjaxscript);
}
&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="thesis"></category><category term="quaternions"></category><category term="linear algebra"></category></entry><entry><title>The Dot Product</title><link href="http://www.josephthurman.com/dotproduct.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-09-12T19:30:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-09-12T19:30:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Joseph Thurman</name></author><id>tag:www.josephthurman.com,2018-09-12:/dotproduct.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Before the hiatus, we began discussing the geometry of vectors in three dimensions.  At the end of &lt;a href="http://www.josephthurman.com/vectorsinR3.html"&gt;that post&lt;/a&gt;, we discussed why it was impossible to define a multiplication operation on &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{R}^3\)&lt;/span&gt; that also has an inverse (division) operation.  However, there are still two useful "product" operations involving …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Before the hiatus, we began discussing the geometry of vectors in three dimensions.  At the end of &lt;a href="http://www.josephthurman.com/vectorsinR3.html"&gt;that post&lt;/a&gt;, we discussed why it was impossible to define a multiplication operation on &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{R}^3\)&lt;/span&gt; that also has an inverse (division) operation.  However, there are still two useful "product" operations involving three-dimensional vectors.  These operations aren't true multiplication operations, in that they don't have an inverse division operation, but they are still useful for understanding three-dimensional geometry. In this post we'll learn about the first of them, the so-called &lt;em&gt;dot product&lt;/em&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Motivation - Distance and Angles&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the last section, we visualized &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{R}^3\)&lt;/span&gt;, the set of triples of real numbers, by considering vectors as arrows in three-dimensional space. Implicit in this description are notions of angle and distance. After all, in order to visualize the vector &lt;span class="math"&gt;\((1, 2, 3)\)&lt;/span&gt; as an arrow in the three-dimensional coordinate system, we need first to set up three perpendicular axes (that is, the angle between each pair of axes is &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(90^\circ\)&lt;/span&gt;), then draw tick marks along each axis at a fixed distance. Said another way, when we do this procedure we are declaring that the vectors &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{e}_1 = (1,0,0), \mathbf{e}_2 = (0,1,0)\)&lt;/span&gt;, and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{e}_3 = (0,0,1)\)&lt;/span&gt; should be understood geometrically as arrows of unit length that are pairwise perpendicular. As a note on terminology, we say that the collection of vectors &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{e}_1, \mathbf{e}_2, \mathbf{e}_3\)&lt;/span&gt; is an &lt;em&gt;orthonormal basis&lt;/em&gt;. "Orthonormal" is a combination of &lt;em&gt;orthogonal&lt;/em&gt;, which is a synonym for perpendicular, while &lt;em&gt;normal&lt;/em&gt; means that each vector is of unit length. ("Basis" has a technical meaning that we don't need to get into right now.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The important point here is that this is an extra piece of information. Considered on its own, the triple of numbers &lt;span class="math"&gt;\((1,2,3)\)&lt;/span&gt; has no inherent geometrical meaning. Similarly, considering &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{R}^3\)&lt;/span&gt; as just a set of triples of real numbers gives it no geometrical meaning.  Geometry requires some notion of measurement of distances - after all, the word geometry itself comes from Greek for "Earth measurement". We have to make some extra choices to give the set &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{R}^3\)&lt;/span&gt; geometric structure. One possible choice is to declare that the vectors &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{e}_1, \mathbf{e}_2,\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{e}_3\)&lt;/span&gt; are to be considered orthonormal. This allows us to consider all vectors as arrows, and then consider angles and distances in the usual way.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, this choice allows us to say that then length of the vector &lt;span class="math"&gt;\((1,2,3)\)&lt;/span&gt; is &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\sqrt{14}\)&lt;/span&gt;. We can find this by repeatedly using the Pythagorean theorem, as illustrated below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Finding Lengths in R3" src="http://www.josephthurman.com/distanceinr3.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Finding Vector Lengths in&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{R}^3\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this picture, the two black lines run parallel to the &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(x\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(y\)&lt;/span&gt; axes, so are easily seen to have lengths 1 and 2.  They form a right triangle, with hypotenuse of length &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\sqrt{1^2 + 2^2} = \sqrt{5}\)&lt;/span&gt; by the Pythagorean theorem.  This hypotenuse is shown in orange.  The orange and blue lines themselves form a right triangle, of which the red vector &lt;span class="math"&gt;\((1,2,3)\)&lt;/span&gt; is the hypotenuse.  The blue line is parallel to the &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z\)&lt;/span&gt; axis, so we can see that it has length &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(3\)&lt;/span&gt;, and so the red vector has length
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
\sqrt{ \sqrt{5}^2 + 3^3 } = \sqrt{5 + 9} = \sqrt{14}
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
as we said before. We could use a similar procedure of breaking down vectors into their components in the &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(x, y, z\)&lt;/span&gt; directions (which are the same as the &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{e}_1, \mathbf{e}_2, \mathbf{e}_3\)&lt;/span&gt; directions) to find the length of any vector &lt;span class="math"&gt;\((v_1, v_2, v_3)\)&lt;/span&gt;, which we will write as &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\|\mathbf{v} \|\)&lt;/span&gt;, to be
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
\|\mathbf{v} \| = \sqrt{v_1^2 + v_2^2 + v_3^2}
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Similarly, we could also find angles between vectors using similar arguments. These methods for computing lengths and angles are unified and made simpler using an operation called the &lt;em&gt;dot product&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Definition of the Dot Product&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given two vectors &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{v} = (v_1, v_2, v_3)\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{w} = (w_1, w_2, w_3)\)&lt;/span&gt;, we define their dot product to be the number
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
\mathbf{v} \cdot \mathbf{w} = v_1 w_1 + v_2 w_2 + v_3 w_3
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First, notice that this product operation is of a different type than the multiplication operation we wish that we could define.  The dot product operation takes in two vectors and returns a single number. A multiplication operation that generalized the multiplication of complex numbers to three dimensions would be an operation that takes in two (3-dimensional) vectors and returned a third vector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the formula, it is easy to check that this product operation has many of the nice properties we might expect. It is &lt;em&gt;commutative&lt;/em&gt;, that is,
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
\mathbf{v} \cdot \mathbf{w} = \mathbf{w} \cdot \mathbf{v},
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
and is &lt;em&gt;distributive&lt;/em&gt; with respect to vector addition, that is,
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
(\mathbf{v}_1 + \mathbf{v}_2) \cdot \mathbf{w} = \mathbf{v}_1 \cdot \mathbf{w} + \mathbf{v}_2 \cdot \mathbf{w}
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above, the dot product can be used to measure distances and angles. First, it can be used to find the length of a vector, since
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
\mathbf{v} \cdot \mathbf{v} = v_1^2 + v_2^2 + v_3^2 = \|\mathbf{v} \|^2,
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
that is, taking the dot product of a vector with itself gives the square of the length.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This allows us to find distances more generally. Given two points &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(p_1, p_2\)&lt;/span&gt; in three-dimensional space, we can consider the vectors &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{w}_1, \mathbf{w}_2\)&lt;/span&gt; that go from the origin to those points.  The difference &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{w}_2 - \mathbf{w}_1\)&lt;/span&gt; is a vector pointing from &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(p_1\)&lt;/span&gt; to &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(p_2\)&lt;/span&gt;, and so the length of the vector gives the distance between those point. If we use &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(d(\mathbf{w}_1, \mathbf{w}_2)\)&lt;/span&gt; to denote the distance between the endpoints of the vectors &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{w}_1, \mathbf{w}_2\)&lt;/span&gt;, we have that
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
d(\mathbf{w}_1, \mathbf{w}_2) = \| \mathbf{w}_2 - \mathbf{w}_1 \|
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can also use the dot product to find the angle between two vectors. Given two vectors &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{v}\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{w}\)&lt;/span&gt;, the angle &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\theta\)&lt;/span&gt; between these two vectors is given by the formula
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
\cos \theta = \frac{\mathbf{v} \cdot \mathbf{w}}{\|\mathbf{v}\| \, \|\mathbf{w}\|}
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As a special case, we can see that this means that &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{v} \cdot \mathbf{w} = 0\)&lt;/span&gt; exactly when &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\theta = 90^\circ\)&lt;/span&gt;, i.e., when the two vectors are orthogonal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why is this formula for the dot product correct? It goes back to the fact that the distances and angles are determined by declaring &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{e}_1 = (1,0,0), \mathbf{e}_2 = (0,1,0),\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{e_3} = (0,0,1)\)&lt;/span&gt; to be orthonormal.  We've defined the formula for the dot product exactly to make this so.  For example,
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
\mathbf{e}_1 \cdot \mathbf{e}_1 = 1^2 + 0^2 + 0^2 = 1,
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
as needed, and
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
\mathbf{e_2} \cdot \mathbf{e}_3 = 0 \cdot 0 + 1 \cdot 0 + 0 \cdot 1 = 0,
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
with similar statements for the other vectors &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{e}_2, \mathbf{e}_3\)&lt;/span&gt; and the other pairs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Generalizations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This definition of the dot product in three dimensions has a number of different generalizations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, we observe that in our arguments above we gave &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{R}^3\)&lt;/span&gt; a geometric structure by declaring a set of orthonormal vectors &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{e}_1, \mathbf{e}_2, \mathbf{e}_3\)&lt;/span&gt;.  We then showed that the distances and angles between vectors that arise from those choices can be summarized by the dot product.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This also works in reverse.  Given the set &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{R}^3\)&lt;/span&gt;, we can define a dot product on &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{R}^3\)&lt;/span&gt; as above, and then use that dot product to define lengths and angles.  With distances and angles defined in this way, the vectors &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{e}_1, \mathbf{e}_2, \mathbf{e}_3\)&lt;/span&gt; are orthonormal. Defining a dot product and defining an orthonormal basis are essentially equivalent processes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of giving a space a geometry by defining a dot product can be generalized to the notion of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inner_product_space"&gt;inner product spaces&lt;/a&gt;. These are sets equipped with an operation called an "inner product" that behaves like the dot product, which gives a way to measure lengths and distances in that space.  We'll return to inner product spaces later in this series.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, although we defined the dot product for three-dimensional vectors since we're considering product operations in three dimensions, we can in fact define a dot product operation for any of the spaces &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{R}^k\)&lt;/span&gt; we defined in the previous post.  Given two elements of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{v} = (v_1, \ldots, v_k)\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{w} = (w_1, \ldots, w_k)\)&lt;/span&gt; of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{R}^k\)&lt;/span&gt;, their dot product is
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
\mathbf{v} \cdot \mathbf{w} = v_1 w_1 + \cdots + v_k w_k
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The set &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{R}^k\)&lt;/span&gt; along with the geometric structure that arises from the dot product is called "&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(K\)&lt;/span&gt;-dimensional Euclidean space." It is named after &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euclid"&gt;Euclid&lt;/a&gt;, the ancient Greek mathematician who formalized the standard, two-dimensional geometry taught in high school. These geometries are all examples of the flat geometries discussed in the &lt;a href="http://www.josephthurman.com/first-series-explaining-my-thesis.html"&gt;introductory post&lt;/a&gt; in this series.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This dot product is just one way, however, to take the set &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{R}^k\)&lt;/span&gt; and define a geometric structure on it that allows us to compute the distance between two points. Using other distance functions can give us other, curved geometries, analogous to the sphere or saddle depicted in that introductory post. This will be hugely important later, but we'll get to that after we finish describing the geometrical interpretation of the quaternions that we're working toward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Next Time - The Cross Product&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dot product is a product operation that takes in two vectors and returns a number, and is used to measure distances and angles in &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{R}^3\)&lt;/span&gt; so that we can consider the geometry of that space. There is a second product operation on &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{R}^3\)&lt;/span&gt;, however, that takes in two vectors and gives back a third vector.  This "cross product" is the final piece of 3-dimensional geometry we'll need to be able to understand the 4-dimensional quaternions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;if (!document.getElementById('mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#')) {
    var align = "center",
        indent = "0em",
        linebreak = "false";

    if (false) {
        align = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "left" : align;
        indent = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "0em" : indent;
        linebreak = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? 'true' : linebreak;
    }

    var mathjaxscript = document.createElement('script');
    mathjaxscript.id = 'mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#';
    mathjaxscript.type = 'text/javascript';
    mathjaxscript.src = 'https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.0/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML';
    mathjaxscript[(window.opera ? "innerHTML" : "text")] =
        "MathJax.Hub.Config({" +
        "    config: ['MMLorHTML.js']," +
        "    TeX: { extensions: ['AMSmath.js','AMSsymbols.js','noErrors.js','noUndefined.js'], equationNumbers: { autoNumber: 'AMS' } }," +
        "    jax: ['input/TeX','input/MathML','output/HTML-CSS']," +
        "    extensions: ['tex2jax.js','mml2jax.js','MathMenu.js','MathZoom.js']," +
        "    displayAlign: '"+ align +"'," +
        "    displayIndent: '"+ indent +"'," +
        "    showMathMenu: true," +
        "    messageStyle: 'normal'," +
        "    tex2jax: { " +
        "        inlineMath: [ ['\\\\(','\\\\)'] ], " +
        "        displayMath: [ ['$$','$$'] ]," +
        "        processEscapes: true," +
        "        preview: 'TeX'," +
        "    }, " +
        "    'HTML-CSS': { " +
        "        styles: { '.MathJax_Display, .MathJax .mo, .MathJax .mi, .MathJax .mn': {color: 'inherit ! important'} }," +
        "        linebreaks: { automatic: "+ linebreak +", width: '90% container' }," +
        "    }, " +
        "}); " +
        "if ('default' !== 'default') {" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('HTML-CSS Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax['HTML-CSS'].FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('SVG Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax.SVG.FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
        "}";
    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(mathjaxscript);
}
&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="thesis"></category><category term="quaternions"></category><category term="linear algebra"></category></entry><entry><title>Geometry of Three-Dimensional Vectors</title><link href="http://www.josephthurman.com/vectorsinR3.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-04-30T12:01:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-04-30T12:01:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Joseph Thurman</name></author><id>tag:www.josephthurman.com,2018-04-30:/vectorsinR3.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://www.josephthurman.com/geometryofcomplexnumbers1.html"&gt;previous&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.josephthurman.com/geometryofcomplexnumbers2.html"&gt;posts&lt;/a&gt; in this series discussed two-dimensional vector geometry and how that geometry can be connected to the algebra of complex numbers.  The main result is that the multiplication of complex numbers corresponds geometrically to rotations and dilations of the 2-dimensional plane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in an &lt;a href="http://www.josephthurman.com/quaternions2.html"&gt;earlier post&lt;/a&gt;, this …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://www.josephthurman.com/geometryofcomplexnumbers1.html"&gt;previous&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.josephthurman.com/geometryofcomplexnumbers2.html"&gt;posts&lt;/a&gt; in this series discussed two-dimensional vector geometry and how that geometry can be connected to the algebra of complex numbers.  The main result is that the multiplication of complex numbers corresponds geometrically to rotations and dilations of the 2-dimensional plane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in an &lt;a href="http://www.josephthurman.com/quaternions2.html"&gt;earlier post&lt;/a&gt;, this geometrical interpretation leads to a natural attempt at generalization. If the complex number system can be used to describe two-dimensional geometry, is there a similar number system that can describe three-dimensional geometry? As that post mentioned, that's not quite the case. Instead, one has to increase to four dimensions, where the desired number system is known as the quaternions. The quaternions can still be used to gain some insight into three-dimensional geometry, however.  In order to understand those connections, we'll take the next few posts to discuss the relevant geometry in three dimensions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3-Dimensional Vectors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real numbers, &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{R}\)&lt;/span&gt;, are one-dimensional, and so an element of the set of real numbers is given by a single number. A two-dimensional quantity is something that is represented by a pair of real numbers. For example, the complex numbers &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{C}\)&lt;/span&gt; are two dimensional, and we write a complex number &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z\)&lt;/span&gt; as &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z = x + y i\)&lt;/span&gt; for &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(x, y\)&lt;/span&gt; real numbers. An element of a three-dimensional space, then, can be represented by three real numbers, which we usually write as &lt;span class="math"&gt;\((x,y,z)\)&lt;/span&gt;.  The set of ordered triples of real numbers is referred to as &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{R}^3\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More generally, we can consider the set &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{R}^k\)&lt;/span&gt; as the set of ordered &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(k\)&lt;/span&gt;-tuples of real numbers. For small values of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(k\)&lt;/span&gt;, we have that &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{R}, \mathbb{R}^2,\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{R}^3\)&lt;/span&gt; correspond to the familiar notion of a line, a plane, and a space.  Larger values of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(k\)&lt;/span&gt; are much more difficult to visualize.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the case of the plane, when &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(k = 2\)&lt;/span&gt;, we've also earlier considered the complex numbers &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{C}\)&lt;/span&gt; as a plane, and we've seen that we can consider a complex number &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z = x + yi\)&lt;/span&gt; as the ordered pair &lt;span class="math"&gt;\((x,y)\)&lt;/span&gt;. This means that &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{C}\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{R}^2\)&lt;/span&gt; actually represent the same set. Why do we use two different symbols for the same set? When we write &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{R}^2\)&lt;/span&gt;, we're just considering the set of ordered pairs of numbers, which doesn't have a natural multiplication operation like the complex numbers do.  We therefore need to use a separate symbol, &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{C}\)&lt;/span&gt;, when we want to consider pairs of real numbers as complex numbers that have an additional multiplication operation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is common in mathematics - we can often give the same underlying object (the set of pairs of real numbers) additional layers of structure (a multiplication operation) to create something new.  In fact, the quaternions are another example of this type of construction. Using the definition above, an element of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{R}^4\)&lt;/span&gt; is an ordered list &lt;span class="math"&gt;\((x_1, x_2, x_3, x_4)\)&lt;/span&gt; of 4 real numbers. A quaternion is also a list of four real numbers, &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(q = x_1 + x_2 i + x_3 j + x_4 k\)&lt;/span&gt;.  But the quaternions have an extra multiplication operation, and so we use the symbol &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{R}^4\)&lt;/span&gt; when we want to consider the set of ordered quadruplets of numbers, and the symbol &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{H}\)&lt;/span&gt; when we want to consider the set of ordered quadruplets of numbers &lt;em&gt;along with&lt;/em&gt; the additional quaternionic multiplication operation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Considering three dimensions, the standard way of visualizing elements &lt;span class="math"&gt;\((x,y,z)\)&lt;/span&gt; in &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{R}^3\)&lt;/span&gt; is as points graphed on a plot with three axes. This is illustrated below, where we graph the points &lt;span class="math"&gt;\((1,2,3)\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\((0,-2,-1)\)&lt;/span&gt;.  Here we're using the standard conventions for drawing three-dimensional graphs on a flat 2-dimensional screen. The positive &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(x\)&lt;/span&gt;-axis is pointing down and to the left, which you should visualize as pointing out of the screen.  The positive &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(y\)&lt;/span&gt;-axis points to the right, and the positive &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z\)&lt;/span&gt;-axis points up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Points plotted in 3D" src="http://www.josephthurman.com/pointsin3d.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Points plotted in 3D&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3-Dimensional Vector Addition&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Points in three-dimensional space can also be considered as vectors, just as we did in two dimensions. Instead of considering the point &lt;span class="math"&gt;\((x,y,z)\)&lt;/span&gt; as just a point, we visualize it as an arrow starting at the origin &lt;span class="math"&gt;\((0,0,0)\)&lt;/span&gt; and pointing to the point &lt;span class="math"&gt;\((x,y,z)\)&lt;/span&gt;.  The is pictured below, where we consider the same points graphed above as vectors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Vectors plotted in 3D" src="http://www.josephthurman.com/vectorsin3d.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vectors plotted in 3D&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The vector addition operation we discussed in two dimensions also generalizes naturally to three-dimensions.  There's an intuitive way to add elements of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{R}^3\)&lt;/span&gt;, by just adding the corresponding elements in the ordered triples:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
(x_1, y_1, z_1) + (x_2, y_2, z_2) = (x_1 + x_2, y_1 + y_2, z_1 + z_2)
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For the two points we've considered above, we have
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
(1,2,3) + (0,-2,-1) = (1,0,2)
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This operation also has the same geometric meaning - if we consider the ordered triples as vectors, then addition corresponds to moving one arrow to begin at the end of the other, then drawing a new vector to the end of that arrow.  This is clearer in pictures, shown below.  The red vector is &lt;span class="math"&gt;\((1,2,3)\)&lt;/span&gt;, the blue vector is &lt;span class="math"&gt;\((0,-2,-1)\)&lt;/span&gt; and the sum &lt;span class="math"&gt;\((1,0,2)\)&lt;/span&gt; is shown in black. The translates of the vectors are also shown to demonstrate that the parallelogram rule similarly applies in 3-dimensions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Vector addition in 3D" src="http://www.josephthurman.com/vectoradditionin3d.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vector addition in 3D&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This addition operation generalizes naturally to all higher dimensions - we can always add two element of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{R}^k\)&lt;/span&gt; by considering those elements as ordered &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(k\)&lt;/span&gt;-tuples of numbers and just adding the corresponding numbers.  (In four dimensions, this exactly gives the operation of addition of quaternions, but we'll discuss this more later.) This becomes difficult, if not impossible, to visualize in higher dimensions, though.  The set &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{R}^k\)&lt;/span&gt;, along with this vector addition operation, is the main example of a &lt;em&gt;vector space&lt;/em&gt;, an extremely important concept in geometry that we'll discuss in more depth in a later post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We see that the set of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{R}^3\)&lt;/span&gt; of triples of real numbers can be given an addition operation, and an inverse subtraction operation is also easy to define: we just subtract the corresponding elements in the triples.  Taking a different set of vectors to subtract, if we have the vectors &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(v_1 = (-1,1,3)\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(v_2 = (1,2,2)\)&lt;/span&gt;, then the subtraction &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(v_1 - v_2\)&lt;/span&gt; results in the vector
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
(-1,1,3) - (1,2,2) = (-2,-1,1)
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This also has an easy interpretation in terms of vectors - subtracting a vector is the same as adding a vector pointing in the opposite direction.  This is illustrated below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Vector subtraction in 3D" src="http://www.josephthurman.com/vectorsubtractionin3d.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vector subtraction in 3D&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In these images, the red vector is &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(v_1\)&lt;/span&gt;, the blue vector is &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(v_2\)&lt;/span&gt;, and the black vector corresponds to the subtraction &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(v_1 - v_2\)&lt;/span&gt;, which we'll call &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(v_3\)&lt;/span&gt;.  The green vector is the vector &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(-v_2 = (-1,-2,-2)\)&lt;/span&gt;, the vector with the same magnitude as &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(v_2\)&lt;/span&gt; but pointing in the opposite direction.  Note that the subtraction &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(v_1 - v_2\)&lt;/span&gt; is the same as the vector addition &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(v_1 + (-v_2)\)&lt;/span&gt;, as illustrated in the left figure.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The image on the right gives another way to interpret the subtraction.  We have that &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(v_1 - v_2 = v_3\)&lt;/span&gt;, which we can rearrange to say that &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(v_1 = v_3 + v_2\)&lt;/span&gt;, which is the vector addition shown on the right.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What About Multiplication and Division?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recall that all our work so far has been to try to understand number systems that have addition, subtraction, multiplication, and division operations. We've done half of that work in &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{R}^3\)&lt;/span&gt; by defining a way to add and subtract triples of real numbers, and this operation corresponds geometrically to vector addition and subtraction.  What happens when we try to define multiplication and division operations?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned earlier, it turns out this is impossible - one has to increase to four dimensions and consider the quaternions in order to be able to define a higher-dimensional number system that has a valid multiplication and division operation.  Proving exactly why such an operation can't exist in three dimensions will have to wait for a later post, but in order to understand this impossibility it's worth it to try to see what happens when we attempt to make such a definition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In particular, we could try to make the most obvious definition for multiplication - what if we just multiply two triples by multiplying their corresponding entries? That is, we can define a multiplication operation by
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
(x_1, y_1, z_1) \cdot (x_2, y_2, z_2) = (x_1x_2, y_1y_2, z_1z_2)
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This certainly defines some kind of operation, but the problem is that there is no way to define a corresponding inverse or division operation for this multiplication.  To see why, consider the multiplication below:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
(1,0,1) \cdot (0,1,0) = (0,0,0)
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Call the two vectors that we've defined &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(v_1\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(v_2\)&lt;/span&gt;, and let &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{0}\)&lt;/span&gt; denote the vector that consists of all zeros, so that we can write the above in a shorter form as &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(v_1 \cdot v_2 = \mathbf{0}\)&lt;/span&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We'd like to define an inverse for &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(v_2\)&lt;/span&gt;, which we would denote by &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(v_2^{-1}\)&lt;/span&gt;, such that multiplication by &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(v_2^{-1}\)&lt;/span&gt; undoes multiplication by &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(v_2\)&lt;/span&gt;.  If we could do that, then we'd be able to write&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
v_1 \cdot v_2 = \mathbf{0} \text{ implies } v_1 \cdot v_2 \cdot v_2^{-1} = \mathbf{0} \cdot v_2^{-1}
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
and since &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(v_2^{-1}\)&lt;/span&gt; undoes multiplication by &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(v_2\)&lt;/span&gt; we'd end up with the expression
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
v_1 = \mathbf{0} \cdot v_2^{-1}
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
But this can't possibly be true - no matter what the vector &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(v_2^{-1}\)&lt;/span&gt; is, it's clear that multiplying it by &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{0}\)&lt;/span&gt; will always result in &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{0}\)&lt;/span&gt;, and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(v_1\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbf{0}\)&lt;/span&gt; are not the same thing.  There's simply no way to define a vector &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(v_2^{-1}\)&lt;/span&gt; that will undo multiplication by &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(v_2\)&lt;/span&gt; using this definition of a multiplication operation.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a more general terminology for this phenomenon - if a set has an multiplication operation and it's possible to multiply two non-zero objects together and obtain zero, then the multiplication is said to have &lt;em&gt;zero divisors&lt;/em&gt;.  And the same argument above applies in general - if a multiplication operation has zero-divisors, it's not possible to define an inverse operation that defines division. With a bit more advanced math (that we might see in a later post), one can show that any multiplication operation on &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{R}^3\)&lt;/span&gt; has to have zero divisors, and so it is impossible to define a multiplication operation on &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{R}^3\)&lt;/span&gt; that also has a corresponding division operation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Next Time: Vector Products in Three Dimensions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not to say that there are no useful concepts of "multiplication" or "product" in three dimensions.  In fact, there are two, and they may be familiar to those who have learned either physics. They are the &lt;em&gt;dot product&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;cross product&lt;/em&gt;, named for the symbols used to write them. Of course, these operations don't have a corresponding division operation, but that doesn't mean they can't still be useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the next posts, we'll learn what these products are and see why they're important to geometry in three dimensions.  These products will also provide the crucial link between the three-dimensional geometry we have been discussing and the 4-dimensional geometry of the quaternions.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;if (!document.getElementById('mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#')) {
    var align = "center",
        indent = "0em",
        linebreak = "false";

    if (false) {
        align = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "left" : align;
        indent = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "0em" : indent;
        linebreak = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? 'true' : linebreak;
    }

    var mathjaxscript = document.createElement('script');
    mathjaxscript.id = 'mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#';
    mathjaxscript.type = 'text/javascript';
    mathjaxscript.src = 'https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.0/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML';
    mathjaxscript[(window.opera ? "innerHTML" : "text")] =
        "MathJax.Hub.Config({" +
        "    config: ['MMLorHTML.js']," +
        "    TeX: { extensions: ['AMSmath.js','AMSsymbols.js','noErrors.js','noUndefined.js'], equationNumbers: { autoNumber: 'AMS' } }," +
        "    jax: ['input/TeX','input/MathML','output/HTML-CSS']," +
        "    extensions: ['tex2jax.js','mml2jax.js','MathMenu.js','MathZoom.js']," +
        "    displayAlign: '"+ align +"'," +
        "    displayIndent: '"+ indent +"'," +
        "    showMathMenu: true," +
        "    messageStyle: 'normal'," +
        "    tex2jax: { " +
        "        inlineMath: [ ['\\\\(','\\\\)'] ], " +
        "        displayMath: [ ['$$','$$'] ]," +
        "        processEscapes: true," +
        "        preview: 'TeX'," +
        "    }, " +
        "    'HTML-CSS': { " +
        "        styles: { '.MathJax_Display, .MathJax .mo, .MathJax .mi, .MathJax .mn': {color: 'inherit ! important'} }," +
        "        linebreaks: { automatic: "+ linebreak +", width: '90% container' }," +
        "    }, " +
        "}); " +
        "if ('default' !== 'default') {" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('HTML-CSS Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax['HTML-CSS'].FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('SVG Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax.SVG.FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
        "}";
    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(mathjaxscript);
}
&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="thesis"></category><category term="quaternions"></category><category term="linear algebra"></category></entry><entry><title>Geometry of the Complex Numbers: Rotations</title><link href="http://www.josephthurman.com/geometryofcomplexnumbers2.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-03-23T11:30:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-03-23T11:30:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Joseph Thurman</name></author><id>tag:www.josephthurman.com,2018-03-23:/geometryofcomplexnumbers2.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href="http://www.josephthurman.com/geometryofcomplexnumbers1.html"&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; in this series, we introduced a geometrical interpretation of the complex numbers as vectors in the 2-dimensional plane.  That post also explained the geometrical significance of the addition of complex numbers as vector addition. In this post, we'll see how to interpret the multiplication of complex …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href="http://www.josephthurman.com/geometryofcomplexnumbers1.html"&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; in this series, we introduced a geometrical interpretation of the complex numbers as vectors in the 2-dimensional plane.  That post also explained the geometrical significance of the addition of complex numbers as vector addition. In this post, we'll see how to interpret the multiplication of complex numbers geometrically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Polar Coordinates in the Plane&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although we didn't make this explicit in the last post, our discussion of complex numbers as points or vectors in the two-dimensional plane has so far used two different coordinate systems.  We first used the standard Cartesian coordinate system, plotting the real part of the complex number on the horizontal axis and the imaginary part on the vertical axis. This description works equally well if we consider the complex number as just a point or as a vector by drawing an arrow from the origin to that point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last post also discussed vectors in a physical context, as a way to interpret change in location (displacement), and in that context we instead described the vector using the &lt;em&gt;magnitude&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;direction&lt;/em&gt; of the vector (e.g., traveling 5 miles southeast).  Of course, this method gives us a way to name points as well - given a vector, the point that the vector describes is just the endpoint of the vector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This method for naming points in the plane is known as the &lt;em&gt;polar coordinate system&lt;/em&gt;. Instead of describing points using distances along perpendicular axes, this system describes points using the distance from a central point and the angle formed with some reference direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to explain polar coordinates we'll briefly put aside the complex numbers and just consider points in the plane as determined by &lt;span class="math"&gt;\((x,y)\)&lt;/span&gt; coordinates. Given a point &lt;span class="math"&gt;\((x,y)\)&lt;/span&gt; in Cartesian coordinates, what are its coordinates in the polar coordinate system?  The relationship is pictured below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Polar Coordinate System" src="http://www.josephthurman.com/polarcoordinates.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Polar Coordinate System&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(r\)&lt;/span&gt; (taken from radius) is the distance from the origin (the magnitude), and the Greek letter theta (&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\theta\)&lt;/span&gt;) gives the direction, as a counterclockwise angle from the positive x-axis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This way to describe angles is different from the way we described directions in the last post.  There, we used compass headings: due north was &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(0^\circ\)&lt;/span&gt;, which would correspond to the direction of the positive &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(y\)&lt;/span&gt;-axis.  In the polar coordinate system, the positive &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(y\)&lt;/span&gt;-axis is at &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(90^\circ\)&lt;/span&gt;.  Similarly, the positive &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(x\)&lt;/span&gt;-axis is the &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(0^\circ\)&lt;/span&gt; direction in the polar coordinate system, but it is measured as &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(90^\circ\)&lt;/span&gt;, or due east, with compass headings. The reference direction used to measure the angles doesn't ultimately make any real difference, so we'll use the traditional mathematical conventions of measuring angles starting from the positive &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(x\)&lt;/span&gt;-axis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of conventions, it's also worth pointing out that mathematicians generally use &lt;em&gt;radians&lt;/em&gt; instead of degrees to measure angles.  If once around the circle measures an angle of 360 degrees, the same angle is &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(2\pi\)&lt;/span&gt; radians. For example, a right angle is either &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(90^\circ\)&lt;/span&gt; or &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\pi/2\)&lt;/span&gt; radians. The distinction between measuring angles in degrees or radians can actually make an important difference in some situations (it's important in calculus, for example), but we won't encounter any such situations in this post, and so  we'll mostly stick to degrees since they are more intuitive to most people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In equations, the relationship is as follows. Given a point &lt;span class="math"&gt;\((x,y)\)&lt;/span&gt; in Cartesian coordinates, its description in polar coordinates is
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
r = \sqrt{x^2 + y^2} \hspace{.25in} \theta = \arctan(y/x)
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
where &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\arctan(x)\)&lt;/span&gt; is the inverse tangent function.  Conversely, given a point &lt;span class="math"&gt;\((r,\theta)\)&lt;/span&gt; in polar coordinates, its description in Cartesian coordinates is
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
x = r \cos \theta \hspace{.25in} y = r \sin \theta
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(r = 1\)&lt;/span&gt;, then this relationship above is exactly the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unit_circle#Trigonometric_functions_on_the_unit_circle"&gt;unit circle&lt;/a&gt; definition of the sine and cosine functions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Polar Form of Complex Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can now go back to considering complex numbers. So far, we've described complex numbers in terms of Cartesian coordinates. For the complex number &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z = a + bi\)&lt;/span&gt;, the real part &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(a\)&lt;/span&gt; gives to coordinate along the horizontal axis and the imaginary part &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(b\)&lt;/span&gt; gives the coordinate along the vertical axis.  Using the equations above, we can instead describe the complex number as a pair of numbers &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(r\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\theta\)&lt;/span&gt; in a polar coordinate system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the formulas, we have that &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(r = \sqrt{a^2 + b^2}\)&lt;/span&gt;. We've already encountered this expression before - this number is the same as &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\sqrt{z \bar{z}}\)&lt;/span&gt;, where &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\bar{z} = a - bi\)&lt;/span&gt; is the complex conjugate of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z\)&lt;/span&gt;. We also used the symbol &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(|z|\)&lt;/span&gt; to denote this value.  In this context, the number &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(|z|\)&lt;/span&gt; is called the &lt;em&gt;modulus&lt;/em&gt; of the complex number &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z\)&lt;/span&gt;. The value &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\theta = \arctan(y/x)\)&lt;/span&gt; also has a special name in the context of complex numbers, and is called the &lt;em&gt;argument&lt;/em&gt; of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z\)&lt;/span&gt;, sometimes denoted by &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\text{arg}(z)\)&lt;/span&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We therefore now have two different ways to describe a complex number. The first method uses its real and imaginary part, which corresponds to the &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z = a+bi\)&lt;/span&gt; description and Cartesian coordinates. The second method uses the modulus and argument, which correspond to magnitude and direction in polar coordinates.  Using the formula to convert polar coordinates to Cartesian coordinates, we can write
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
z = |z|(\cos \theta + i \sin \theta)
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
to express complex numbers in their so-called &lt;em&gt;polar form&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Depending on the situation, one of these forms is usually a more convenient way to express complex numbers.  For example, we've already seen that adding complex numbers in the Cartesian coordinate expression is fairly straightforward.  If &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z_1 = a_1 + b_1 i\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z_2 = a_2 + b_2 i\)&lt;/span&gt;, then
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
z_1 + z_2 = (a_1 + a_2) + (b_1 + b_2)i
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It's not so easy to add complex numbers in polar form, however. If one were instead told only the modulus and argument of the complex numbers &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z_1, z_2\)&lt;/span&gt;, then it's not immediately clear how to find the modulus and argument of the complex number &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z_1 + z_2\)&lt;/span&gt;. The easiest way to find these values is usually to convert both &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z_1\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z_2\)&lt;/span&gt; to their Cartesian coordinate expression, add them as above, and then convert back to polar form.  (This is probably familiar to anyone whose main exposure to vectors is high-school physics.  In that context, vectors are often given using magnitude and direction, and one of the easiest ways to add vectors in such a context is to find the &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(x\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(y\)&lt;/span&gt; components of the vectors and add those separately. Finding the &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(x\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(y\)&lt;/span&gt; components of a vector is exactly the same process as converting it from polar form to Cartesian form.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, we saw in &lt;a href="http://www.josephthurman.com/quaternions1.html"&gt;a previous post&lt;/a&gt; that the multiplication of complex numbers, written in Cartesian coordinates, isn't exactly intuitive.  The formula is that
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
(a_1 + b_1 i)(a_2 + b_2 i) = (a_1 a_2 - b_1 b_2) + (a_1 b_2 + a_2 b_1) i,
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
which arises from treating &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(i\)&lt;/span&gt; as a variable and gathering like terms, using the simplification that &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(i^2 = -1\)&lt;/span&gt;.  This formula, though, will become much clearer when we consider the expression for the multiplication of complex numbers in polar form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Multiplication of Complex Numbers in Polar Form&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how do we multiply complex numbers in polar form? If &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z_1, z_2\)&lt;/span&gt; are complex numbers, with moduli &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(|z_1|, |z_2|\)&lt;/span&gt; and arguments &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\theta_1, \theta_2\)&lt;/span&gt;, respectively, then their product is
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{align*}
z_1 z_2 &amp;amp;= |z_1|(\cos \theta_1  + i \sin \theta_1)|z_2|(\cos \theta_2  + i \sin \theta_2) \\
  &amp;amp;= |z_1||z_2|\Big( \big((\cos \theta_1)(\cos \theta_2)- (\sin \theta_1)(\sin \theta_2)\big) + i\big((\cos \theta_1)(\sin \theta_2) + (\sin \theta_1)(\cos \theta_2)\big) \Big)
\end{align*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This expression looks complicated, but can be simplified with a little knowledge of trigonometry.  There are formulas that allow one to express the sine and cosine of the sum of two angles in terms of the sine and cosine of the angles being addded.  Specifically, the following formulas are true for any pair of angles &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\theta_1, \theta_2\)&lt;/span&gt;:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{align*}
\sin(\theta_1 + \theta_2) &amp;amp;= (\cos \theta_1)(\sin \theta_2) + (\sin \theta_1)(\cos \theta_2) \\
\cos(\theta_1 + \theta_2) &amp;amp;= (\cos \theta_1)(\cos \theta_2)- (\sin \theta_1)(\sin \theta_2)
\end{align*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Of course, these are exactly the expressions appearing above, and so we can finally express our multiplication formula in polar form as
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
z_1 z_2 = |z_1| |z_2| \big(\cos(\theta_1 + \theta_2) + i \sin(\theta_1 + \theta_2)\big)
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is the polar form for a complex number with modulus &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(|z_1| |z_2| = |z_1 z_2|\)&lt;/span&gt; and argument &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\theta_1 + \theta_2\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don't remember the various trigonometry identities, then understanding the derivation of the formula we gave above isn't really that important. What is important is that this formula finally gives a way to interpret the multiplication of complex numbers geometrically. We see that to multiply two complex numbers &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z_1\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z_2\)&lt;/span&gt; in polar form, we multiply their respective moduli and add their arguments.  This means that multiplication of complex numbers corresponds geometrically to &lt;em&gt;stretching&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;rotating&lt;/em&gt; vectors in the the plane.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's illustrate this with a simple example. Let &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z = \sqrt{3}
 - i\)&lt;/span&gt;, and let &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(w = -2 + 2 \sqrt{3}i\)&lt;/span&gt;.  These are expressed in Cartesian form now, but using the formulas above one can show that in polar form
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{align*}
z &amp;amp;= 2 \left(\cos(-30^\circ) + i \sin(-30^\circ) \right)\\
w &amp;amp;= 4 \left( \cos(120^\circ) + i \sin(120^\circ) \right)
\end{align*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
that is, &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z\)&lt;/span&gt; has modulus &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(|z| = 2\)&lt;/span&gt; and argument &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(-30^\circ\)&lt;/span&gt;, and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(w\)&lt;/span&gt; has modulus &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(|w| = 4\)&lt;/span&gt; and argument &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(120^\circ\)&lt;/span&gt;.  The product &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(zw\)&lt;/span&gt; therefore has modulus &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(|zw| = 2 \cdot 4 = 8\)&lt;/span&gt; and argument &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(120 - 30 = 90^\circ\)&lt;/span&gt;, and so can be expressed in polar form as
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
zw = 8 \left( \cos(90^\circ) + i \sin(90^\circ) \right)
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Expressed in Cartesian coordinates, this is
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
zw = 8i
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
which could also be obtained by multiplying the expressions for &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(w\)&lt;/span&gt; in Cartesian coordinates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The geometrical interpretation is clearer when we plot &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z\)&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(w\)&lt;/span&gt;, and their product &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(zw\)&lt;/span&gt; as vectors in the plane:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Geometrical interpretation of complex multiplication " src="http://www.josephthurman.com/vectormultiplication1.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vector representation of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z\)&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(w\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(zw\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note in the image above that the length of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(zw\)&lt;/span&gt; is 4 times the length of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z\)&lt;/span&gt;, and twice the length of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(w\)&lt;/span&gt;.  The angles are a little harder to judge in this picture, but they match up as well - the angle between the &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(zw\)&lt;/span&gt; and the positive &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(x\)&lt;/span&gt;-axis is the sum the the angles that the vectors &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(w\)&lt;/span&gt; make with that axis (the former angle being negative).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's also helpful to think of multiplication as a transformation that one vector is performing on the other.  For example, we could consider the product &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(zw\)&lt;/span&gt; as taking the vector &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z\)&lt;/span&gt; and transforming it by the action represented by the complex number &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(w\)&lt;/span&gt;.  That is, as &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(w\)&lt;/span&gt; has a modulus of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(4\)&lt;/span&gt; and an argument of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(120^\circ\)&lt;/span&gt;, it represents a transformation that consists of stretching any other vector to 4 times its length, then rotating it counterclockwise by &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(120^\circ\)&lt;/span&gt;.  This is illustrated in the left picture below. This picture is the same as the picture above, but we mark the angles explicitly.  Notice that the dashed red angle, which is the angle that we rotate &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z\)&lt;/span&gt; by to obtain the direction of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(zw\)&lt;/span&gt;, is the same as the blue angle, the argument of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(w\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Complex Multiplication as Rotation and Stretching " src="http://www.josephthurman.com/vectormultiplication2.png"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Complex multiplication as a transformation of the plane&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, we could just as well consider the product &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(zw\)&lt;/span&gt; as changing the vector &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(w\)&lt;/span&gt; by the transformation represented by &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z\)&lt;/span&gt;.  As the modulus of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z\)&lt;/span&gt; is 2 and its argument is &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(-30^\circ\)&lt;/span&gt;, this transformation consists of stretching by 2 and then rotating clockwise by &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(30^\circ\)&lt;/span&gt;.  This is illustrated in the right picture above, where we see that the blue dashed angle that we must rotate &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(w\)&lt;/span&gt; by to obtain the direction of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(zw\)&lt;/span&gt; has the same measure as the red angle, the argument of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's worth it to use this interpretation of complex numbers as transformations of the plane to think about the complex number &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(i\)&lt;/span&gt; again.  Under this interpretation, the complex number &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(i\)&lt;/span&gt; corresponds to rotating the plane counterclockwise by &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(90^\circ\)&lt;/span&gt;. This means that the number &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(i^2\)&lt;/span&gt; corresponds to rotation by &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(90^\circ\)&lt;/span&gt;, followed by rotation by &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(90^\circ\)&lt;/span&gt;, that is, rotation by &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(180^\circ\)&lt;/span&gt;. Of course, if you take the real axis and rotate it &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(180^\circ\)&lt;/span&gt;, the effect will be that every number will move to its opposite , e.g., 2 will move to &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(-2\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(-4\)&lt;/span&gt; will move to 4. This transformation is the same as multiplying every real number by &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(-1\)&lt;/span&gt;. Therefore the algebraic expression &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(i^2 = -1\)&lt;/span&gt;, which before maybe seemed a little strange (how can the square of something be negative?) makes sense when considered geometrically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Euler's Formula&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is already a little long, and we've already explained the most important point for our future work, but it would be mathematical malpractice for me to discuss the multiplication of complex numbers without discussing "Euler's identity," which is considered by many to be one of the most beautiful equations in all of mathematics. Euler's identity is
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
e^{i \pi} + 1 = 0.
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This equation is famous for giving a simple relationship between 5 of the most important numbers in mathematics: Euler's number &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(e\)&lt;/span&gt;, the circle constant &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\pi\)&lt;/span&gt;, the imaginary unit &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(i\)&lt;/span&gt;, the additive identity &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(0\)&lt;/span&gt;, and the multiplicative identity &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(1\)&lt;/span&gt;. (The equation could be more succinctly written as &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(e^{i \pi } = -1\)&lt;/span&gt;, but we cheat a little bit to be able to consider &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(0\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(1\)&lt;/span&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This identity is actually a special case of a more general formula called Euler's formula.  Given a real number &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\theta\)&lt;/span&gt;, which we interpret as an angle measured in radians, we have that
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
e^{i \theta} = \cos \theta + i \sin \theta
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If we use this formula with the specific value of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\theta = \pi\)&lt;/span&gt;, we obtain the special identity above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now, we basically have to take this formula as a definition of what &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(e^{i\theta}\)&lt;/span&gt; means, so that &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(e^{i\theta}\)&lt;/span&gt; is a different way to write the complex number with modulus 1 and argument &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\theta\)&lt;/span&gt;.  Using the interpretation we developed in the previous section, this means that &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(e^{i\theta}\)&lt;/span&gt; is another way to represent the transformation of counterclockwise rotation by an angle of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\theta\)&lt;/span&gt;.  This formula also gives us another way to write complex numbers in polar form - a complex number with modulus &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(r\)&lt;/span&gt; and argument &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\theta\)&lt;/span&gt; is can be written succinctly as &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z = re^{i\theta}\)&lt;/span&gt;.  In this notation, the process of multiplication of complex numbers matches with the rules of multiplying expressions with exponents
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
(r_1 e^{i\theta_1})(r_2 e^{i\theta_2}) = r_1 r_2 e^{i(\theta_1 + \theta_2)}
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Described in this way, this formula perhaps doesn't seem very special - it's basically just a notational convenience.  Truly understanding why this formula is correct and interesting requires calculus, and we won't get into that in this post.  But as a first step down that path, the reader who remembers what a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taylor_series#List_of_Maclaurin_series_of_some_common_functions"&gt;Maclaurin series expansion&lt;/a&gt; is encouraged to consider the Maclaurin series for &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(e^{x}\)&lt;/span&gt; with &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(x\)&lt;/span&gt; replaced with &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(i \theta\)&lt;/span&gt; and compare the resulting expression to the Maclaurin series for &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\cos\theta, \sin\theta\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Summary, and on to the Quaternions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post marks the end of our consideration of complex numbers, at least for now.  It's therefore helpful to summarize what we've discussed so far:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Complex numbers are numbers of the form &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(a +bi\)&lt;/span&gt;, where &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(i^2 = -1\)&lt;/span&gt;.  Algebraically, they are interesting because they allow us to solve polynomial equations that don't have any real number solutions, like &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(x^2 + 1 = 0\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Geometrically, complex numbers can be visualized as points or vectors in the two-dimensional plane, with their real part &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(a\)&lt;/span&gt; plotted along the horizontal axis and their imaginary part &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(b\)&lt;/span&gt; plotted along the vertical axis.  They can also be described using polar coordinates, in which case the distance from the origin is called the modulus and the angle with the positive real axis is called the argument.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Complex addition, when interpreted geometrically, is vector addition. Translate one vector to the tip of the other, and the sum vector is obtained by drawing an arrow from the base of the second to the tip of the first.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Complex multiplication, interpreted geometrically, is a transformation that consists of taking the vector associated to one of the complex numbers and then stretching and rotating it using the modulus and argument of the other complex number.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what's next? Complex numbers give a compact way to describe geometric transformations in two dimensions, which leads to the question: what about three dimensions? Is there a way to define a multiplication operation of three-dimensional objects or vectors that has a natural geometrical interpretation? Can rotations in three dimensions be described neatly in such a way? The answer is yes, and this is done using the quaternions we've already discussed.  In the next series of posts, we'll begin to understand more about vector geometry in three dimensions and how quaternions can be used to describe this geometry.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;if (!document.getElementById('mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#')) {
    var align = "center",
        indent = "0em",
        linebreak = "false";

    if (false) {
        align = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "left" : align;
        indent = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "0em" : indent;
        linebreak = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? 'true' : linebreak;
    }

    var mathjaxscript = document.createElement('script');
    mathjaxscript.id = 'mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#';
    mathjaxscript.type = 'text/javascript';
    mathjaxscript.src = 'https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.0/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML';
    mathjaxscript[(window.opera ? "innerHTML" : "text")] =
        "MathJax.Hub.Config({" +
        "    config: ['MMLorHTML.js']," +
        "    TeX: { extensions: ['AMSmath.js','AMSsymbols.js','noErrors.js','noUndefined.js'], equationNumbers: { autoNumber: 'AMS' } }," +
        "    jax: ['input/TeX','input/MathML','output/HTML-CSS']," +
        "    extensions: ['tex2jax.js','mml2jax.js','MathMenu.js','MathZoom.js']," +
        "    displayAlign: '"+ align +"'," +
        "    displayIndent: '"+ indent +"'," +
        "    showMathMenu: true," +
        "    messageStyle: 'normal'," +
        "    tex2jax: { " +
        "        inlineMath: [ ['\\\\(','\\\\)'] ], " +
        "        displayMath: [ ['$$','$$'] ]," +
        "        processEscapes: true," +
        "        preview: 'TeX'," +
        "    }, " +
        "    'HTML-CSS': { " +
        "        styles: { '.MathJax_Display, .MathJax .mo, .MathJax .mi, .MathJax .mn': {color: 'inherit ! important'} }," +
        "        linebreaks: { automatic: "+ linebreak +", width: '90% container' }," +
        "    }, " +
        "}); " +
        "if ('default' !== 'default') {" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('HTML-CSS Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax['HTML-CSS'].FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('SVG Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax.SVG.FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
        "}";
    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(mathjaxscript);
}
&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="thesis"></category><category term="quaternions"></category><category term="complex numbers"></category></entry><entry><title>Vectors and the Complex Numbers</title><link href="http://www.josephthurman.com/geometryofcomplexnumbers1.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-03-14T18:30:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-03-14T18:30:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Joseph Thurman</name></author><id>tag:www.josephthurman.com,2018-03-14:/geometryofcomplexnumbers1.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href="http://www.josephthurman.com/quaternions2.html"&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, we first encountered the quaternions, giving an essentially algebraic definition by defining a quaternion as a set of four real numbers and defining operations to add, subtract, multiply, and divide these quadruplets.  But my thesis work is in geometry, not algebra, and so it still remains …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href="http://www.josephthurman.com/quaternions2.html"&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, we first encountered the quaternions, giving an essentially algebraic definition by defining a quaternion as a set of four real numbers and defining operations to add, subtract, multiply, and divide these quadruplets.  But my thesis work is in geometry, not algebra, and so it still remains to understand why the quaternions are interesting from a geometric perspective.  Uncovering the geometry associated to the quaternions will be the goal of the next few posts in this series.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before considering the geometry of the quaternions, though, it will be helpful to understand the geometry of the complex numbers first.  In the same way that understanding the algebraic properties of the &lt;a href="http://www.josephthurman.com/quaternions1.html"&gt;complex numbers&lt;/a&gt; made it easier to understand the quaternions, we'll see that it will be much easier to understand the quaternions if we understand the simpler, 2-dimensional geometry of the complex numbers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, we'll describe the method for understanding complex numbers as geometric objects and consider the interpretation of the addition of complex numbers in this setting. In our next post, we'll extend these insights to understand the geometrical significance of complex multiplication.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Complex Numbers as 2-Dimensional Vectors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recall from that earlier post that the set of complex numbers &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{C}\)&lt;/span&gt; is the set of numbers of the form &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z = a + bi\)&lt;/span&gt;, where &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(a, b\)&lt;/span&gt; are real numbers and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(i^2 = -1\)&lt;/span&gt; is the imaginary unit.  In that post we also gave methods to add, subtract, multiply, and divide complex numbers, that is, we described the algebraic properties of the complex numbers.  To understand the geometric properties of the complex numbers, we need a way to picture them.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We already have a geometric understanding of the real numbers, as the set of points along a number line.  Since complex numbers consist of a pair of real numbers, we can picture them using a pair of number lines. Putting one of those number lines perpendicular to the other, we have a standard pair of axes that we can use to plot points that represent complex numbers.  This pair of axes is just like the usual Cartesian coordinate system, or &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(xy\)&lt;/span&gt;-plane, that is used for graphing functions. In this context, though, we consider the horizontal axis to be the &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; axis, where we plot the value of the real part (denoted by &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(a\)&lt;/span&gt; above) of the complex number, and the vertical axis is the &lt;em&gt;imaginary&lt;/em&gt; axis, where we plot the value of the imaginary part (denoted by &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(b\)&lt;/span&gt;).  This is illustrated below, where we show the 2-dimensional plane representing the complex numbers and plot a variety of points on that plane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The Complex Plane" src="http://www.josephthurman.com/complexplane.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Complex Plane&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of just considering complex numbers as points, we can also consider them as &lt;em&gt;vectors&lt;/em&gt;. Geometrically, this means that we can think of a complex number &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z = a+bi\)&lt;/span&gt; as not a point but an arrow, beginning at the origin of the plane (the point &lt;span class="math"&gt;\((0,0)\)&lt;/span&gt;, or the complex number &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(0 + 0i\)&lt;/span&gt;, where the two axes intersect) and extending to the point &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(a+bi\)&lt;/span&gt;.  Illustrating this with the same points we plotted above gives the following plot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Vectors in the Complex Plane" src="http://www.josephthurman.com/complexvectors.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vectors in the Complex Plane&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One way to think about vectors is to consider how they are used in physics, where there is a distinction made between &lt;em&gt;scalar&lt;/em&gt; quantities and &lt;em&gt;vector&lt;/em&gt; quantities.  Scalar quantities are those that can be specified with a single number, like mass or temperature.  Vector quantities, on the other hand, require multiple numbers, often interpreted as a &lt;em&gt;magnitude&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;direction&lt;/em&gt;. For example, velocity is a vector quantity, because it consists of both a magnitude, which is called speed (e.g., 60 miles per hour) and a direction of movement (e.g., due north). A velocity (in two dimensions) could be pictured as an arrow in the plane, as above, where one imagines the moving object at the center of the plane, with the arrow pointing in its direction of movement and the length of the arrow corresponding to speed (longer being faster).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Vector Addition&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another example of a vector quantity is change in position, which in physics is called &lt;em&gt;displacement&lt;/em&gt;. If a person begins at one location, and after some amount of time ends up in a different location, then we can describe their movement by two numbers, the magnitude of the distance between the locations (e.g., 5 miles) and the direction that they traveled (south east, perhaps).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This leads to a natural problem - how to combine changes in position? For example, a person could begin at home, then travel 5 miles southeast to go to school, and then travel 2 miles northeast to go to work. What is their final location relative to their starting position, that is, relative to home? Put another way, if they wanted to travel directly to work, how far should they travel and in what direction?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can find the answer fairly easily by plotting the various locations. We can draw a standard 2-dimensional coordinate system, and place the "home" location at the origin.  We can then draw an arrow depicting the change in position from home to school, shown in red in the picture below, and likewise for the change from school to work, shown in blue below.  We can then draw an arrow from the origin to the head of the blue arrow, and this arrow represents the change in position to go directly from home to work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Vector Addition for Changing Locations" src="http://www.josephthurman.com/vectoraddition1.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vector Addition for Changing Locations&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With a little computation involving some trigonometry (that will be discussed more in depth in the next post) the black vector has a magnitude of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\sqrt{29} \approx 5.4\)&lt;/span&gt; and the direction, as a compass heading (with north as &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(0^\circ\)&lt;/span&gt;, east as &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(90^\circ\)&lt;/span&gt;, etc), is about &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(113^\circ\)&lt;/span&gt;, or roughly east-southeast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The blue arrow as drawn above represents a change in position from school to work.  However, the starting point isn't really important when one considers change in position - all that really matters is that the blue arrow really represents a change in location of traveling 2 miles to the north-east. In fact, all of the above discussion doesn't really have anything to do with the particular starting point - if you start at one spot, then move southeast 5 miles, then move northeast two miles, you'll always end up in the position relative to the starting point of about 5.4 miles away, roughly east-southeast.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is important because when we consider vectors from an abstract mathematical perspective, we always draw them as starting from the origin. Thus, instead of drawing the blue arrow as beginning from the end of the red arrow, we'll draw it as beginning at the origin if we want to consider it as an abstract vector.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, we can restate the entire problem in terms of abstract vectors, without thinking of them as related to any particular location. Let &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(v\)&lt;/span&gt; denote the red vector, as it was drawn above, and let &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(w\)&lt;/span&gt; denote the blue vector, which we will now draw as starting from the origin. Then the black vector is called the vector sum &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(v+w\)&lt;/span&gt;.  This is illustrated below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Abstract Vector Addition" src="http://www.josephthurman.com/vectoraddition2.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Abstract Vector Addition&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This image gives us the rule to add vectors abstractly, which is called the parallelogram rule.  To add vectors, we can draw from the end of the first vector an arrow that has the same length and direction as the second.  The sum vector is then the vector that joins the base of the first arrow to the head of the second. There are two ways to do this, depending on which vector you start with, though both choices give the same result. Note that the two vectors determine a parallelogram, and the sum vector is the diagonal of that parallelogram, hence the name of the rule. In this picture the dotted arrows shown do not represent vectors, since they do not begin at the origin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Addition of Complex Numbers is Vector Addition&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we saw above, we can consider complex numbers as vectors, and so vector addition gives us a second way to add complex numbers - we can add them either as complex numbers with the addition procedure defined in the earlier post, or as vectors.  The important point is that both operations are actually the same. Let's illustrate this with an example.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z = 3+ 2i\)&lt;/span&gt;, and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(w = -2 + i\)&lt;/span&gt;.  Using the rule for the addition of complex numbers, we have that the sum is &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z + w = 1 + 3i\)&lt;/span&gt;.  If we consider &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z, w\)&lt;/span&gt;, and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z + w\)&lt;/span&gt; as vectors, we have the following picture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Vector Addition of Complex Numbers" src="http://www.josephthurman.com/vectoraddition3.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vector Addition of Complex Numbers&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this particular example, we see that vector addition and complex addition give the same result.  Although we won't formally prove it here, it's not hard to see that this is true for any pair of complex numbers. Thus, if we use our geometrical interpretation of concept number as vectors, we have a geometrical interpretation of the process of addition. Conversely, we could take any problem involving two-dimensional vectors, like the change in position problem above, and restate it in terms of complex numbers.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Next Time - The Geometrical Significance of Multiplication&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of this, however, really makes use of the special properties of complex numbers, and complex numbers aren't necessary to understand vectors in two dimensions.  In fact, many people learn about vectors in a high-school physics without ever learning about complex numbers. All of the above work would be no different if we just considered vectors as pairs of numbers &lt;span class="math"&gt;\((a,b)\)&lt;/span&gt; instead of as pairs of numbers &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(a + bi\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The truly interesting features of the complex numbers come into play when one considers multiplication, not addition, and make use of the defining fact of complex numbers that &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(i^2 = -1\)&lt;/span&gt;.  In the next post, we'll see how to interpret the multiplication of complex numbers geometrically.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;if (!document.getElementById('mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#')) {
    var align = "center",
        indent = "0em",
        linebreak = "false";

    if (false) {
        align = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "left" : align;
        indent = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "0em" : indent;
        linebreak = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? 'true' : linebreak;
    }

    var mathjaxscript = document.createElement('script');
    mathjaxscript.id = 'mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#';
    mathjaxscript.type = 'text/javascript';
    mathjaxscript.src = 'https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.0/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML';
    mathjaxscript[(window.opera ? "innerHTML" : "text")] =
        "MathJax.Hub.Config({" +
        "    config: ['MMLorHTML.js']," +
        "    TeX: { extensions: ['AMSmath.js','AMSsymbols.js','noErrors.js','noUndefined.js'], equationNumbers: { autoNumber: 'AMS' } }," +
        "    jax: ['input/TeX','input/MathML','output/HTML-CSS']," +
        "    extensions: ['tex2jax.js','mml2jax.js','MathMenu.js','MathZoom.js']," +
        "    displayAlign: '"+ align +"'," +
        "    displayIndent: '"+ indent +"'," +
        "    showMathMenu: true," +
        "    messageStyle: 'normal'," +
        "    tex2jax: { " +
        "        inlineMath: [ ['\\\\(','\\\\)'] ], " +
        "        displayMath: [ ['$$','$$'] ]," +
        "        processEscapes: true," +
        "        preview: 'TeX'," +
        "    }, " +
        "    'HTML-CSS': { " +
        "        styles: { '.MathJax_Display, .MathJax .mo, .MathJax .mi, .MathJax .mn': {color: 'inherit ! important'} }," +
        "        linebreaks: { automatic: "+ linebreak +", width: '90% container' }," +
        "    }, " +
        "}); " +
        "if ('default' !== 'default') {" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('HTML-CSS Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax['HTML-CSS'].FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('SVG Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax.SVG.FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
        "}";
    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(mathjaxscript);
}
&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="thesis"></category><category term="quaternions"></category><category term="complex numbers"></category></entry><entry><title>Introducing the Quaternions</title><link href="http://www.josephthurman.com/quaternions2.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-03-01T20:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-03-01T20:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Joseph Thurman</name></author><id>tag:www.josephthurman.com,2018-03-01:/quaternions2.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In our last post we laid the foundation necessary to understand the quaternions, a 4-dimensional number system with some interesting properties that are applicable in higher-dimensional geometry.  We didn't actually define or discuss the quaternions in &lt;a href="http://www.josephthurman.com/quaternions1.html"&gt;that post&lt;/a&gt;, but instead discussed the real and complex numbers.  It might be helpful …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In our last post we laid the foundation necessary to understand the quaternions, a 4-dimensional number system with some interesting properties that are applicable in higher-dimensional geometry.  We didn't actually define or discuss the quaternions in &lt;a href="http://www.josephthurman.com/quaternions1.html"&gt;that post&lt;/a&gt;, but instead discussed the real and complex numbers.  It might be helpful to go back and skim that post again, especially the section defining the operations with complex numbers, as many of the properties of the quaternions are analogous to properties of the complex numbers.  With that preparation, though, we're finally ready to introduce and define the quaternions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Quaternions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We saw that the complex numbers can be constructed by considering a new number &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(i\)&lt;/span&gt; with the property that &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(i^2 = -1\)&lt;/span&gt;, and then defining addition and multiplication of numbers of the form &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(a + bi\)&lt;/span&gt; in a natural way. But why stop there? We can define other new numbers, which we'll denote by &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(j\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(k\)&lt;/span&gt;, and consider numbers of the form &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(a + bi + cj + dk\)&lt;/span&gt; where &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(a,b,c,d\)&lt;/span&gt; are real numbers.  We call the collection of numbers of this form the &lt;em&gt;quaternions&lt;/em&gt;, which we denote by &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{H}\)&lt;/span&gt;.  Here &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{H}\)&lt;/span&gt; stands for Hamilton, as in &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Rowan_Hamilton"&gt;William Rowan Hamilton&lt;/a&gt;, the Irish mathematician who first constructed the quaternions. (The perhaps more natural &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{Q}\)&lt;/span&gt; is already taken, as this is used to denote the rational numbers.) We can see that the quaternions extend the complex numbers &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{C}\)&lt;/span&gt;, since we can consider a complex number &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(a+bi\)&lt;/span&gt; as a quaternion &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(a + bi + 0j + 0k\)&lt;/span&gt; where the &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(j, k\)&lt;/span&gt; part of the quaternion are simply 0.  The quaternions are evidently a four-dimensional number system, as a single quaternion actually represents a set of four real numbers.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the form &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(q = a + bi + cj + dk\)&lt;/span&gt; it is easy to see how to add quaternions.  We have, for two quaternions &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(q_0, q_1\)&lt;/span&gt;, that
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
q_0 + q_1 = (a_0 + b_0i + c_0j + d_0k) + (a_1 + b_1i + c_1j + d_1 k) = (a_0 + a_1) + (b_0 + b_1)i + (c_0 + c_1)j + (d_0 + d_1)k,
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
that is, we can add quaternions simply by "adding like terms."  Subtraction of quaternions is defined similarly.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more difficult property to define is multiplication.  As in the case of the complex numbers, the crucial point is to understand how to define multiplication amongst the "new" numbers &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(i, j, k\)&lt;/span&gt;.  The appropriate multiplication rules are what Hamilton discovered when he constructed the quaternions.  Apparently he was walking with his wife one day along a canal in Dublin when he suddenly realized the correct multiplication rule, and he was so excited that he immediately carved the formula into a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History_of_quaternions#Hamilton's_discovery"&gt;bridge along the canal&lt;/a&gt;:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
i^2 = j^2 = k^2 = ijk = -1
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here we use juxtaposition to denote multiplication, that is, &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(ij\)&lt;/span&gt; means the same thing as &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(i \times j\)&lt;/span&gt;. We'll sometimes also denote multiplication with a small dot, e.g., &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(i \cdot j\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above multiplication rule is more commonly written in the equivalent form
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
i^2 = j^2 = k^2 = -1 \text{ and } ij = k = -ji.
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This latter form makes the most important feature of quaternion multiplication more obvious: it is &lt;em&gt;not commutative&lt;/em&gt;.  We say an operation is commutative if the order of the operands does not matter.  For example, addition of real numbers is commutative because &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(a + b = b + a\)&lt;/span&gt; for all real numbers.  Likewise the multiplication of real numbers is commutative, as are both addition and multiplication of complex numbers. Subtraction of real numbers is not commutative, since in general &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(a - b \neq b - a\)&lt;/span&gt;.  To say that quaternionic multiplication is not commutative is to say that if &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(p, q\)&lt;/span&gt; are quaternions, then in general we have that &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(p q \neq q p\)&lt;/span&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using the above rules for multiplying the elements &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(i, j, k\)&lt;/span&gt;, we can define the product of any two quaternions in a way that's very similar to the method for the complex numbers, by treating &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(i, j, k\)&lt;/span&gt; as variables but simplifying any multiplication between these numbers using the multiplication rules above.  After a simple but somewhat tedious computation, we arrive at the following general formula for multiplication of any two quaternions:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{align*}
q_0 q_1 &amp;amp;= (a_0 + b_0i + c_0j + d_0k) \cdot (a_1 + b_1i + c_1j + d_1k) \\
&amp;amp;= (a_0 a_1 - b_0 b_1 -c_0 c_1 - d_0 d_1)+ (a_1 b_0 + a_0 b_1 - c_1 d_0 + c_0 d_1) i \\
 &amp;amp;\hspace{.25in}+ (a_1 c_0 + a_0 c_1 + b_1 d_0 - b_0 d_1)j + (-b_1 c_0 + b_0 c_1 + a_1 d_0 + a_0 d_1)k
\end{align*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we'd like to consider quaternionic division as well.  Similar to the complex case, we will actually define an inverse operation, and again this will be based on a conjugation operation.  If &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(q = a + bi + cj +dk\)&lt;/span&gt; is a quaternion, then we will call &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(a\)&lt;/span&gt; the &lt;em&gt;real part&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(bi + cj + dk\)&lt;/span&gt; the &lt;em&gt;imaginary part&lt;/em&gt;, and once again the complex conjugation operation will consist of switching the sign of the imaginary part, that is
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
\overline{q} = a - bi - cj - dk
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Just as in the case of complex numbers, we can observe that &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(|q|^2 = q \overline{q} = a^2 + b^2 + c^2 +d^2\)&lt;/span&gt; is a real number (i.e., has no imaginary part), and that the inverse of a quaternion will be given by
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
q^{-1} = \frac{1}{|q|^2}\overline{q} = \frac{a}{a^2+b^2+c^2+d^2} + \frac{-b}{a^2+b^2+c^2+d^2}i + \frac{-c}{a^2+b^2+c^2+d^2}j + \frac{-d}{a^2+b^2+c^2+d^2}k
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fractions of quaternions, are actually not exactly defined since multiplication is not commutative.  If we'd like to take the quaternionic fraction &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\frac{q}{p}\)&lt;/span&gt;, then, using the understanding that "division" means the same thing as "multiplying by the inverse", the value of the division should be the same as the number obtained by multiplying &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(q\)&lt;/span&gt; by &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(p^{-1}\)&lt;/span&gt;.  However there are two ways to do this multiplication, either &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(p^{-1}q\)&lt;/span&gt; or &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(qp^{-1}\)&lt;/span&gt;, that will in general not be the same since quaternionic multiplication is not commutative.  Therefore we will never write quaternions as fractions, and instead only consider multiplication by the inverse so that the order of the operands is clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a note on terminology, in the last post we said that the real numbers and the complex numbers are both examples of &lt;em&gt;fields&lt;/em&gt; since they possess addition, subtraction, multiplication, and division operations. One of the additional requirements of a field that went unmentioned in that post is that the multiplication in a field should be commutative. The quaternions are therefore not a field.  Instead, the quaternions are known as a "division algebra." The term "skew field" is also used in older books, but is less common today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;And Beyond&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the previous post, we saw that we could extend the one-dimensional real number system using the two-dimensional complex numbers.  In this post, we extended the complex numbers by the four-dimensional quaternions. Each time, we've managed to extend the number system by doubling the dimension. Could we keep going? Are there further number systems with dimension 8, 16, 32, and so on?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer is yes, although the number systems that arise in this way are not generally as useful.  Each extension process we have discussed so far is an example of a general construction called the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cayley–Dickson_construction"&gt;Cayley-Dickson construction&lt;/a&gt;.  This is a procedure that takes one of the number systems we have been discussing and produces a new number system of twice the dimension.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new number systems constructed by this process, though, always lose some of the desirable algebraic properties of the starting point.  For example, in moving from &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{R}\)&lt;/span&gt; to &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{C}\)&lt;/span&gt;, we lose the property that the real numbers are ordered. Similarly, we lose the commutativity of multiplication when we extend from &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{C}\)&lt;/span&gt; to &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{H}\)&lt;/span&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We could apply the Cayley-Dickson construction again to the quaternions to produce an 8-dimensional number system called the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Octonion"&gt;octonions&lt;/a&gt;. In constructing these numbers, we lose the property of &lt;em&gt;associativity&lt;/em&gt; of multiplication, which is the property that the result of multiplication is independent of the grouping.  That is, given three numbers &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(a, b, c\)&lt;/span&gt;, we could form the product of these numbers in two different ways (fixing the order), as either &lt;span class="math"&gt;\((ab)c\)&lt;/span&gt; or as &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(a(bc)\)&lt;/span&gt;. The reals, complexes, and quaternions are all associative, in that this grouping does not matter, e.g.,
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
(2 \cdot 3) \cdot 4 = 6 \cdot 4 = 24 = 2 \cdot 12 = 2 \cdot (3 \cdot 4)
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is no longer the case for the octonions. Even so, the octonions are still useful in mathematics and also in some physics applications, although we won't discuss the octonions any further.  One can continue past the octonions as well (the next number system is called the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sedenion"&gt;sedenions&lt;/a&gt;) but these further number systems are not commonly studied by mathematicians - after repeating the Cayley-Dickson construction so many times they have lost enough algebraic properties that they are no longer as useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Why the Quaternions?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the above we've seen what the quaternions are from an axiomatic perspective. We've defined a quaternion as a collection of 4 real numbers, and given ways to add, subtract, multiply, and divide quaternions. This is interesting, but it may make the quaternions seem like an odd curiosity. Have we just found a set of weird rules for manipulating quadruplets of numbers, or do the quaternions actually amount to something?.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The complex numbers have something of this flavor, as a weird system for manipulating pairs of numbers. But we saw in the previous post that they actually solve an important problem: they're an algebraically closed extension of the real numbers. What problems were the quaternions meant to solve? Why did Hamilton think they were important enough to vandalize a bridge when he discovered them? In our  next few posts, we'll answer that question, when we see that the quaternions are intimately related with the geometry of rotations in three dimensions.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;if (!document.getElementById('mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#')) {
    var align = "center",
        indent = "0em",
        linebreak = "false";

    if (false) {
        align = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "left" : align;
        indent = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "0em" : indent;
        linebreak = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? 'true' : linebreak;
    }

    var mathjaxscript = document.createElement('script');
    mathjaxscript.id = 'mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#';
    mathjaxscript.type = 'text/javascript';
    mathjaxscript.src = 'https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.0/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML';
    mathjaxscript[(window.opera ? "innerHTML" : "text")] =
        "MathJax.Hub.Config({" +
        "    config: ['MMLorHTML.js']," +
        "    TeX: { extensions: ['AMSmath.js','AMSsymbols.js','noErrors.js','noUndefined.js'], equationNumbers: { autoNumber: 'AMS' } }," +
        "    jax: ['input/TeX','input/MathML','output/HTML-CSS']," +
        "    extensions: ['tex2jax.js','mml2jax.js','MathMenu.js','MathZoom.js']," +
        "    displayAlign: '"+ align +"'," +
        "    displayIndent: '"+ indent +"'," +
        "    showMathMenu: true," +
        "    messageStyle: 'normal'," +
        "    tex2jax: { " +
        "        inlineMath: [ ['\\\\(','\\\\)'] ], " +
        "        displayMath: [ ['$$','$$'] ]," +
        "        processEscapes: true," +
        "        preview: 'TeX'," +
        "    }, " +
        "    'HTML-CSS': { " +
        "        styles: { '.MathJax_Display, .MathJax .mo, .MathJax .mi, .MathJax .mn': {color: 'inherit ! important'} }," +
        "        linebreaks: { automatic: "+ linebreak +", width: '90% container' }," +
        "    }, " +
        "}); " +
        "if ('default' !== 'default') {" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('HTML-CSS Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax['HTML-CSS'].FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('SVG Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax.SVG.FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
        "}";
    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(mathjaxscript);
}
&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="thesis"></category><category term="quaternions"></category></entry><entry><title>On the Way to the Quaternions: Real and Complex Numbers</title><link href="http://www.josephthurman.com/quaternions1.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-02-22T10:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-02-22T10:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Joseph Thurman</name></author><id>tag:www.josephthurman.com,2018-02-22:/quaternions1.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href="http://www.josephthurman.com/first-series-explaining-my-thesis.html"&gt;introductory post&lt;/a&gt; to this series of posts explaining my thesis, we first heard about "quaternion-K&amp;auml;hler manifolds," a type of geometric object with special curvature properties.  These special geometric properties are related to the algebraic properties of the &lt;em&gt;quaternions&lt;/em&gt;, a 4-dimensional number system that generalizes the somewhat more familiar …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href="http://www.josephthurman.com/first-series-explaining-my-thesis.html"&gt;introductory post&lt;/a&gt; to this series of posts explaining my thesis, we first heard about "quaternion-K&amp;auml;hler manifolds," a type of geometric object with special curvature properties.  These special geometric properties are related to the algebraic properties of the &lt;em&gt;quaternions&lt;/em&gt;, a 4-dimensional number system that generalizes the somewhat more familiar real and complex number systems. In this post, we'll lay the groundwork for defining the quaternions by discussing some properties of the real and complex numbers. A good understanding of these two number systems, and especially of the complex numbers, will be necessary to understand the more complicated quaternions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Real Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real number system, often denote in mathematics by the symbol &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{R}\)&lt;/span&gt;, is the number system associated to the concept of the "number line" that is often taught in schools.  That is, if one considers a straight, infinitely long line, then every point on that line can be associated to a number.  We can choose a center point for the line, which we associate to the number 0, and then could repeatedly move to the right by a fixed distance to mark the points associated to 1, 2, 3, etc., and similarly to the left for the points -1, -2, -3, etc.  All other points on this line also represent numbers - the point exactly halfway between -1 and -2 is the point -3/2, while the number &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\pi = 3.14159\ldots\)&lt;/span&gt; is associated to a point that's a little to the right of 3, and so on.  All real numbers can be written as decimals (although those decimals might repeat infinitely, as in &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(1/3 = 0.3333333\ldots\)&lt;/span&gt;, or might even go one forever without any discernible pattern, as in &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\pi\)&lt;/span&gt;), and using these decimal expressions we have methods for adding, subtracting, multiplying and dividing real numbers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The number line" src="http://www.josephthurman.com/numberline.png"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The real number line&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the idea of the real number line is fairly intuitive, the formal mathematical definition of the real numbers is rather complicated, and a great deal of mathematical energy was expended to define and understand the real numbers.  This technical work is in one sense extremely important to my own thesis work, in that it is the foundation for all of calculus and therefore for all of my work.  On the other hand, Newton and Leibniz invented calculus without a mathematically rigorous definition of the real number system, and if they didn't need all of the gory technical details, then we won't spend too much time worrying about them either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that said, we will say a few important facts about the real numbers.  First, the real numbers are a &lt;em&gt;field&lt;/em&gt;, the mathematical word for set equipped with operations that behave like addition, subtraction, multiplication, and division. The abstract definition of a field was essentially made to generalize the structure of the real numbers.  The real number field has two extra properties, though, that make it special.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, it is &lt;em&gt;ordered&lt;/em&gt;, that is, for any two numbers &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(x, y\)&lt;/span&gt; we can always say that either &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(x \leq y\)&lt;/span&gt; or &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(y \leq x\)&lt;/span&gt; (or both if we actually have &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(x = y\)&lt;/span&gt;) and that this order satisfies some extra properties to make it consistent with the addition and multiplication operations. (One of these is that if &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(x \geq 0\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(y \geq 0\)&lt;/span&gt;, then we also have that the product &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(xy \geq 0\)&lt;/span&gt;.)  Not every field is ordered. For example, since the complex numbers discussed below are two dimensional, they do not admit an order that's compatible with the field structure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, the real numbers are &lt;em&gt;Dedekind-complete&lt;/em&gt; with respect to this order. This property is also known as the "least upper bound property." It says that, given any non-empty collection of real numbers that has some upper bound (a number &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(M\)&lt;/span&gt; such that if &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(x\)&lt;/span&gt; is a number in the collection, &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(x \leq M\)&lt;/span&gt;), then that collection has a &lt;em&gt;smallest&lt;/em&gt; upper bound.  This is also not true for every field. In particular, the &lt;em&gt;rational&lt;/em&gt; numbers do not have this property.  The rational numbers are the set of numbers that can be expressed as a ratio of two integers (for example, &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(2\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(-5/4\)&lt;/span&gt; are rational, while &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\pi\)&lt;/span&gt; is not). The rational numbers are also a field, since one can add, subtract, multiply, and divide fractions (and the result is always a fraction), and are in fact an ordered field as well.  They are not, however, Dedekind-complete. To see why, consider the set of all rational numbers less than &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\sqrt{2}\)&lt;/span&gt;. This set is bounded, and it's not hard to see that the least upper bound of this set is &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\sqrt{2}\)&lt;/span&gt;. But &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\sqrt{2}\)&lt;/span&gt; is irrational, so the set of rational numbers does not have the least upper bound property since the least upper bound &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\sqrt{2}\)&lt;/span&gt; is not itself a rational number.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One can show with a fair amount of work that these two properties uniquely determine the real numbers, that is, there is exactly one ordered, Dedekind-complete field. Still, making a formal mathematical construction of a field that satisfies these two properties is not easy, and the interested reader can search the internet for more information on either &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dedekind_cut"&gt;Dedekind cuts&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Construction_of_the_real_numbers#Construction_from_Cauchy_sequences"&gt;Cauchy sequences&lt;/a&gt;. For the future, we'll only need the intuitive understanding of the real numbers as the points along the number line, but it's good to point out the difficulties in defining the real number line as an example of the way that seemingly intuitive concepts can hide a great deal of mathematical complexity.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Complex Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One drawback of the real numbers is that they are not &lt;em&gt;algebraically closed&lt;/em&gt;. This means that not every real polynomial has real roots.  A &lt;em&gt;real polynomial&lt;/em&gt; is an expression with the form
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
p(x) = a_n x^n + a_{n-1} x^{n-1} + \cdots + a_2 x^2 + a_1 x + a_0
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
where the coefficients &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(a_n, \ldots, a_0\)&lt;/span&gt; are real numbers and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(x\)&lt;/span&gt; is a variable.  A &lt;em&gt;root&lt;/em&gt; of a polynomial is a value for &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(x\)&lt;/span&gt; that makes &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(p(x) = 0\)&lt;/span&gt;.  For example, &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(1\)&lt;/span&gt; is a root of the polynomial &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(q(x) = x^2 - 1\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But we can find polynomials with real-number coefficients that do not have any real-number roots, such as
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
p(x) = x^2 + 1
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For any real number &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(x\)&lt;/span&gt;, the square &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(x^2 \geq 0\)&lt;/span&gt;, and so &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(x^2 + 1 &amp;gt; 0\)&lt;/span&gt; and there can be no real roots.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's somewhat inconvenient to have equations involving only real numbers that are still impossible to solve.  To fix this problem, we can define a new number &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(i\)&lt;/span&gt;, called the &lt;em&gt;imaginary unit&lt;/em&gt;, to be a number such that &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(i^2 = -1\)&lt;/span&gt; so that &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(i\)&lt;/span&gt; is a root of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(p(x)\)&lt;/span&gt; above. This leads to the definition of the &lt;em&gt;complex numbers&lt;/em&gt;. A complex number &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z\)&lt;/span&gt; consists of a pair of real numbers &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(a, b\)&lt;/span&gt;, which we call the &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;imaginary&lt;/em&gt; parts, respectively, and we write &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z = a + bi\)&lt;/span&gt;. The set of all complex numbers is denoted by &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{C}\)&lt;/span&gt;.  Note that we can consider the real numbers &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{R}\)&lt;/span&gt; as a subset of the complex numbers: if &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(a\)&lt;/span&gt; is a real number, we can consider it as the complex number &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(a + 0 i\)&lt;/span&gt;, that is, a complex number with no imaginary part. This is a two dimensional number system, since a number in &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{C}\)&lt;/span&gt; actually consists of a &lt;em&gt;pair&lt;/em&gt; of real numbers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The choice of the word "imaginary" to describe these numbers is unfortunate, since it implies that these numbers aren't actually numbers and are just strange mathematical objects someone dreamed up. (This terminology was coined by Ren&amp;eacute; Descartes, of "I think therefore I am" fame, in order to denigrate the complex numbers in exactly this way.) And some would say this criticism makes sense. After all, these numbers are defined so that the equation &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(X^2 + 1 = 0\)&lt;/span&gt; can have a solution, and some might say that this equation obviously has no solutions and it's silly to ask for one.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such objections are based on opinion, though, which doesn't really count for much in formal mathematics.  Worse, the same kind of argument could be used to ignore any number of mathematical topics.  Consider negative numbers: they were introduced to be able to solve equations like, say, &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(X + 5 = 2\)&lt;/span&gt;. But this equation is ridiculous and obviously shouldn't have a solution - after all, if you started with &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(X\)&lt;/span&gt; apples and someone gave you five apples, how could you end with only 2?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arguments about whether or not certain numbers are "real" in a philosophical sense can get surprisingly heated.  Consider for example the irrational numbers, that is, real numbers that are not rational numbers. Actually, if you happen to follow a Pythagorean philosophy, it's probably safer not to. The Pythagorean theorem is named after Pythagoras, an ancient Greek philosopher who also lead something like a cult that was based around mathematical principles.  His and his followers' theology was heavily influenced by music and harmony, where many important concepts like scales and consonance are related to having only whole-number ratios of numbers.  They were so invested in the divine order of rational numbers that it's sometimes said that they denied the existence of irrational numbers, going so far as to &lt;a href="https://io9.gizmodo.com/did-pythagoras-really-murder-a-guy-1460668208"&gt;murder one of their own members&lt;/a&gt; for proving that &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\sqrt{2}\)&lt;/span&gt; is irrational. (The story of the murder probably isn't actually true, partly because there is some disagreement about exactly which irrational number was the cause for the murder. The story linked above says it's the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Golden_ratio"&gt;golden ratio&lt;/a&gt;, but the version with &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\sqrt{2}\)&lt;/span&gt; is also common.) Somewhat ironically, the Pythagoreans would have thought about &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\sqrt{2}\)&lt;/span&gt; because, if a perfect square has a side length of 1, then the length of the diagonal will be &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\sqrt{2}\)&lt;/span&gt;, a fact that one can prove using the Pythagorean theorem.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus if you think it makes sense to talk about negative numbers, or irrational numbers, then you should think it makes perfectly good sense to talk about imaginary numbers and complex numbers as well.  If nothing else, we'll see in a later post that complex numbers can and do have a real physical significance, even if it's less obvious than applications of other number systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Operations with Complex Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With any concerns about the ontological status of the complex numbers brushed aside, we can now define operations with complex numbers. We will define addition, subtraction, multiplication, and division rules for complex numbers so that &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{C}\)&lt;/span&gt; is also a field.  Addition and subtraction are defined in a fairly straightforward way, essentially by considering &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(i\)&lt;/span&gt; as a variable and combining like terms.  That is, if &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z = a + bi\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(w = c + di\)&lt;/span&gt; are complex numbers, then
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
z \pm w = (a + bi) \pm (c + di) = (a \pm c) + (b \pm d)i
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We just add (or subtract) the real parts and the imaginary parts separately.  Multiplication is defined by again treating &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(i\)&lt;/span&gt; as a variable, but also making the simplification that &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(i^2 = -1\)&lt;/span&gt; wherever possible. Therefore we have
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{align*}
z \times w &amp;amp;= (a+bi) \times (c+di) \\
  &amp;amp;= ac + adi + bci + bdi^2 \\
  &amp;amp;= ac + adi + bci - bd \\
  &amp;amp;= (ac - bd) + (ad + bc)i
\end{align*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We'll generally drop the multiplication sign, and denote multiplication just by juxtaposition, i.e., &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(zw\)&lt;/span&gt; means the same as &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z \times w\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To define division of complex numbers, we can consider one extra operation on complex numbers, called &lt;em&gt;complex conjugation&lt;/em&gt;.  Given a complex number &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z = a + bi\)&lt;/span&gt;, then its complex conjugate, denoted by &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\overline{z}\)&lt;/span&gt;, is the complex number &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\overline{z} = a - bi\)&lt;/span&gt;, that is, we switch the sign on the imaginary part of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z\)&lt;/span&gt;.  Complex conjugation is special because the product of a complex number and its complex conjugate is always a real number:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{align*}
z \overline{z} &amp;amp;= (a+bi)(a-bi) \\
  &amp;amp;= a^2 - abi + abi - b^2 i^2 \\
  &amp;amp;= a^2 + b^2
\end{align*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The number &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\sqrt{z \overline{z}} = \sqrt{a^2 + b^2}\)&lt;/span&gt; is also called the &lt;em&gt;norm&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;modulus&lt;/em&gt; of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z\)&lt;/span&gt;, and will be discussed more in a later post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we have defined complex conjugation, we can write the rule for division of complex numbers. It's actually easier to define a different operation, called the &lt;em&gt;inverse&lt;/em&gt; of a complex number.  Given a nonzero complex number &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z\)&lt;/span&gt;, we will define the inverse to be the complex number denoted by &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z^{-1}\)&lt;/span&gt; with the property that &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(zz^{-1} = 1\)&lt;/span&gt;. (Zero has no inverse, since &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(0\)&lt;/span&gt; times any complex number can never be 1. This is ok because division by 0 is not defined anyway). Defining an inverse is the same as defining division, since division is just the operation that  undoes multiplication.  That is, if we have the product &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(wz\)&lt;/span&gt; and want to undo the multiplication by &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z\)&lt;/span&gt;, one way to do so would be to "divide by &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z\)&lt;/span&gt;" to be left with just &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(w\)&lt;/span&gt;.  Since we could also take &lt;span class="math"&gt;\((wz)z^{-1} = w (z z^{-1}) = w (1) = w\)&lt;/span&gt;, we define "division by &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z\)&lt;/span&gt;" to be the same as "multiplication by the inverse &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z^{-1}\)&lt;/span&gt;".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what is the inverse?  Using the conjugation operator, we can define
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
z^{-1} = \frac{1}{|z|^2} \overline{z} = \frac{a}{a^2+b^2} - \frac{b}{a^2 + b^2}i
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To check that this is correct, observe that
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{align*}
zz^{-1} &amp;amp;= (a+bi)\left( \frac{a}{a^2+b^2} - \frac{b}{a^2 + b^2} i \right) \\
  &amp;amp;= \frac{a^2}{a^2 + b^2} - \frac{ab}{a^2 + b^2} i + \frac{ab}{a^2 + b^2} i - \frac{b^2}{a^2+b^2}i^2 \\
  &amp;amp;= \frac{a^2}{a^2 + b^2} + \frac{b^2}{a^2+b^2} = \frac{a^2+b^2}{a^2 + b^2} = 1
\end{align*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we have that the complex numbers are a field, but what are they good for? Returning to the motivation for the construction of the complex numbers in the previous section, one can show that the complex numbers are algebraically closed. That is, any (nonconstant) polynomial with &lt;em&gt;complex&lt;/em&gt; coefficients will always have a complex root.  Since real numbers are themselves a subset of the complex numbers, this means that any polynomial equation with real coefficients can always be solved using complex numbers.  The fact that the complex numbers are algebraically closed is known as the "Fundamental Theorem of Algebra."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This leads to one of the main situations in which a non-mathematician might have encountered complex numbers in school.  Many people learn the quadratic formula, which, given a quadratic equation of the form
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
ax^2 + bx + c = 0,
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
says that the solutions of this equation are given by the pair of values
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
x = \frac{-b \pm \sqrt{b^2 - 4ac}}{2a}
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The first time one encounters this formula, they learn that the number &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(b^2 - 4ac\)&lt;/span&gt; is called the &lt;em&gt;discriminant&lt;/em&gt;, and that the quadratic equation has no solution if this value is negative, since one cannot take the square root of a negative number.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, one can't take the square root of a negative number and obtain a real number, but we've seen that the complex numbers are specifically constructed so that we can take square roots of negative numbers. The imaginary unit &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(i\)&lt;/span&gt; is after all defined to be &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\sqrt{-1}\)&lt;/span&gt;.  By expanding our number system and considering complex numbers, we can therefore see from this formula that all quadratic equations can be solved - we just have to use complex numbers for the solution in the case that the discriminant is negative. The Fundamental Theorem of Algebra, moreover, says that roots can be found for any polynomial, if one allows for complex number solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Next Time - The Quaternions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this understanding of the real and complex number system, we're ready to actually define the quaternions in the next post.  We'll see that they are a four-dimensional extension of the complex numbers that has many of the same properties of the complex numbers, but with a few major differences as well.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;if (!document.getElementById('mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#')) {
    var align = "center",
        indent = "0em",
        linebreak = "false";

    if (false) {
        align = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "left" : align;
        indent = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "0em" : indent;
        linebreak = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? 'true' : linebreak;
    }

    var mathjaxscript = document.createElement('script');
    mathjaxscript.id = 'mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#';
    mathjaxscript.type = 'text/javascript';
    mathjaxscript.src = 'https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.0/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML';
    mathjaxscript[(window.opera ? "innerHTML" : "text")] =
        "MathJax.Hub.Config({" +
        "    config: ['MMLorHTML.js']," +
        "    TeX: { extensions: ['AMSmath.js','AMSsymbols.js','noErrors.js','noUndefined.js'], equationNumbers: { autoNumber: 'AMS' } }," +
        "    jax: ['input/TeX','input/MathML','output/HTML-CSS']," +
        "    extensions: ['tex2jax.js','mml2jax.js','MathMenu.js','MathZoom.js']," +
        "    displayAlign: '"+ align +"'," +
        "    displayIndent: '"+ indent +"'," +
        "    showMathMenu: true," +
        "    messageStyle: 'normal'," +
        "    tex2jax: { " +
        "        inlineMath: [ ['\\\\(','\\\\)'] ], " +
        "        displayMath: [ ['$$','$$'] ]," +
        "        processEscapes: true," +
        "        preview: 'TeX'," +
        "    }, " +
        "    'HTML-CSS': { " +
        "        styles: { '.MathJax_Display, .MathJax .mo, .MathJax .mi, .MathJax .mn': {color: 'inherit ! important'} }," +
        "        linebreaks: { automatic: "+ linebreak +", width: '90% container' }," +
        "    }, " +
        "}); " +
        "if ('default' !== 'default') {" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('HTML-CSS Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax['HTML-CSS'].FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('SVG Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax.SVG.FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
        "}";
    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(mathjaxscript);
}
&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="thesis"></category><category term="quaternions"></category><category term="complex numbers"></category></entry><entry><title>First Series - Explaining my Thesis</title><link href="http://www.josephthurman.com/first-series-explaining-my-thesis.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-02-08T17:08:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-02-08T17:08:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Joseph Thurman</name></author><id>tag:www.josephthurman.com,2018-02-08:/first-series-explaining-my-thesis.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;When you're a mathematics PhD student, your work is likely to be totally inscrutable to just about anyone you meet, even many fellow mathematicians. This is probably true for advanced research work in nearly any field, but I think the problem is especially bad in pure mathematics, largely for two …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When you're a mathematics PhD student, your work is likely to be totally inscrutable to just about anyone you meet, even many fellow mathematicians. This is probably true for advanced research work in nearly any field, but I think the problem is especially bad in pure mathematics, largely for two reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first is that the the objects of study in mathematics are often unfamiliar and, to an outsider at least, hopelessly abstract. As a comparison, one of my brothers is also an academic, working on a PhD in biology and studying evolution in butterflies. The real details of his work are beyond me, but I learned the basics of evolution in high school, and I definitely know what a butterfly is, so he can tell me something about his work and I at least know what he's talking about. In contrast, my academic research involves various constructions related to quaternion-K&amp;auml;hler manifolds, and if you know what that means, congratulations to you on finishing your math PhD!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second problem is that the way that mathematicians think about math, especially the way they do research, is very different from the way that many people learn about mathematics in school. If you stopped learning math in high school or in a first-year calculus course in college, you probably think of math as a collection of formulas to be applied to solving problems on a worksheet. But before those formulas can be used to solve problems, someone has to come up with them, and understand why they work. Even more crucially, someone has to build the logical framework that gives the formulas and their applications context. This is what mathematicians actually do -- they define different abstract logical systems and try to understand their properties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a simple example, consider arithmetic, that is, addition, subtraction, multiplication, and division.  Middle school students learn algorithms like long division to compute these operations, and then spend weeks doing worksheets where they divide various numbers over and over.  This is important to be able to do, but a mathematician would want to ask more questions: for example, what is a number, exactly, and what does it mean to multiply two numbers? A mathematician might notice that multiplication is an operation that takes in two objects from the collection of numbers and produces a third number, subject to various rules - for example, commutativity (that &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(a \times b = b \times a\)&lt;/span&gt;) and distribution over addition (that &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(a \times (b + c) = a \times b + a \times c\)&lt;/span&gt;). They might then try to consider other collections of objects and construct multiplication-like rules for those collections. In particular, the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quaternion"&gt;quaternions&lt;/a&gt;, which feature prominently in my thesis, are a number system constructed by the mathematician William Rowan Hamilton in the process of trying to find a way to "multiply" triples of numbers. Thinking about these abstract structures and trying to deduce their properties is, to a mathematician at least, far more interesting that doing worksheet after worksheet of long division problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is the first in a series that will ultimately attempt to explain the results of my thesis to a general audience (or at least my family, who might be the only people who ever read this). I hope not only to explain the esoteric and abstract objects that I spend most of my time thinking about, but also to demonstrate the way that mathematicians think about math.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before embarking on that journey, though, I'll give the shortest summary of my work that I can. It's common advice for academics of all types to always have an "elevator pitch" explanation of their research that they could give to anyone in under two minutes. Mine goes something like this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Two-Minute Summary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I work in differential geometry, an area of mathematics that studies how to measure distances in spaces, and how spaces can themselves curve and bend. One of the most familiar geometric spaces is a flat, 2-dimensional, infinite plane - basically like a sheet of paper extended out as large as conceivably possible. High school geometry is really the study of this one space - learning about angles, distances, shapes, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are other spaces that one can study, though, with different geometries. As an example, consider the surface of the earth, which (if we imagine that the earth is perfectly smooth) has the geometry of a "round 2-sphere." It is also a two-dimensional geometry, in that you can specify a location on the surface of the earth using two numbers, latitude and longitude, and all the same concepts of geometry still apply - you can still talk about distances between points, angles, shapes on this surface, etc. It is very different from the flat geometry, though. For example, you could (in principle) continually walk in a fixed direction, and in doing so walk around the whole world and end up back at your starting point, which is definitely not possible on the flat plane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main difference between these two geometries is a property called curvature. In two dimensions, there is a number that one can assign to every point of a space that describes how curved that space is at that point. For the flat piece of paper, that number is 0 for every point. For the sphere, that number is positive at every point. In fact, if &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(R\)&lt;/span&gt; is the radius of the sphere, then the curvature is given by &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(1/R^2\)&lt;/span&gt;. For example, the curvature of the earth, which has a large radius, would be a small, but positive number. This agrees with our perception that the earth &lt;em&gt;seems&lt;/em&gt; flat when you walk around, and that you'd have to walk a long way to notice it curving. If you could walk around on the surface of a smaller sphere, like a basketball, you'd definitely notice the curvature. There are also two dimensional spaces of &lt;em&gt;negative&lt;/em&gt; curvature. "Negative" curvature just means that the surface curves in opposite directions. An example is the surface of a horse saddle -- the surface curves down to the ground on the left and right (where your legs go), but curves up to the sky in front and behind. A sphere always curves in the same direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Illustration of Curvature Types" src="http://www.josephthurman.com/3spaces.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Examples of 2-dimensional surfaces with positive, zero, and negative curvature&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These concepts are easy to visualize for two-dimensional surfaces sitting in three-dimensional space (as illustrated above), but most geometry research is concerned with higher dimensions, where things are much more complicated. According to general relativity, for example, the universe is a four-dimensional geometric object, with the three familiar spatial dimensions and an extra time dimension, and the way that this "spacetime" curves determines the gravitational field. The concept of curvature is also more complicated in higher dimensions,  where one needs many numbers to describe the curvature of the space in the many possible different directions, instead of the single number necessary in two dimensions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As stated above, I study "quaternion-K&amp;auml;hler manifolds." These are higher-dimensional geometries, occurring in dimensions divisible by 4 (i.e., 4, 8, 12, ...) that have a very particular type of curvature, that makes them interesting in various mathematical applications and in theoretical physics.  My work on these spaces is an attempt to understand both how many different types of quaternion-K&amp;auml;hler manifolds exist and how these spaces can be used to construct other geometries with interesting curvature properties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;if (!document.getElementById('mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#')) {
    var align = "center",
        indent = "0em",
        linebreak = "false";

    if (false) {
        align = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "left" : align;
        indent = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "0em" : indent;
        linebreak = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? 'true' : linebreak;
    }

    var mathjaxscript = document.createElement('script');
    mathjaxscript.id = 'mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#';
    mathjaxscript.type = 'text/javascript';
    mathjaxscript.src = 'https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.0/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML';
    mathjaxscript[(window.opera ? "innerHTML" : "text")] =
        "MathJax.Hub.Config({" +
        "    config: ['MMLorHTML.js']," +
        "    TeX: { extensions: ['AMSmath.js','AMSsymbols.js','noErrors.js','noUndefined.js'], equationNumbers: { autoNumber: 'AMS' } }," +
        "    jax: ['input/TeX','input/MathML','output/HTML-CSS']," +
        "    extensions: ['tex2jax.js','mml2jax.js','MathMenu.js','MathZoom.js']," +
        "    displayAlign: '"+ align +"'," +
        "    displayIndent: '"+ indent +"'," +
        "    showMathMenu: true," +
        "    messageStyle: 'normal'," +
        "    tex2jax: { " +
        "        inlineMath: [ ['\\\\(','\\\\)'] ], " +
        "        displayMath: [ ['$$','$$'] ]," +
        "        processEscapes: true," +
        "        preview: 'TeX'," +
        "    }, " +
        "    'HTML-CSS': { " +
        "        styles: { '.MathJax_Display, .MathJax .mo, .MathJax .mi, .MathJax .mn': {color: 'inherit ! important'} }," +
        "        linebreaks: { automatic: "+ linebreak +", width: '90% container' }," +
        "    }, " +
        "}); " +
        "if ('default' !== 'default') {" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('HTML-CSS Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax['HTML-CSS'].FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('SVG Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax.SVG.FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
        "}";
    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(mathjaxscript);
}
&lt;/script&gt;</content></entry></feed>