<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Joseph Thurman - Thesis</title><link href="http://www.josephthurman.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.josephthurman.com/feeds/thesis.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.josephthurman.com/</id><updated>2018-03-01T20:00:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>Introducing the Quaternions</title><link href="http://www.josephthurman.com/quaternions2.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-03-01T20:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-03-01T20:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Joseph Thurman</name></author><id>tag:www.josephthurman.com,2018-03-01:/quaternions2.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In our last post we laid the foundation necessary to understand the quaternions, a 4-dimensional number system with some interesting properties that are applicable in higher-dimensional geometry.  We didn't actually define or discuss the quaternions in &lt;a href="http://www.josephthurman.com/quaternions1.html"&gt;that post&lt;/a&gt;, but instead discussed the real and complex numbers.  It might be helpful …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In our last post we laid the foundation necessary to understand the quaternions, a 4-dimensional number system with some interesting properties that are applicable in higher-dimensional geometry.  We didn't actually define or discuss the quaternions in &lt;a href="http://www.josephthurman.com/quaternions1.html"&gt;that post&lt;/a&gt;, but instead discussed the real and complex numbers.  It might be helpful to go back and skim that post again, especially the section defining the operations with complex numbers, as many of the properties of the quaternions are analogous to properties of the complex numbers.  With that preparation, though, we're finally ready to introduce and define the quaternions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Quaternions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We saw that the complex numbers can be constructed by considering a new number &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(i\)&lt;/span&gt; with the property that &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(i^2 = -1\)&lt;/span&gt;, and then defining addition and multiplication of numbers of the form &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(a + bi\)&lt;/span&gt; in a natural way. But why stop there? We can define other new numbers, which we'll denote by &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(j\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(k\)&lt;/span&gt;, and consider numbers of the form &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(a + bi + cj + dk\)&lt;/span&gt; where &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(a,b,c,d\)&lt;/span&gt; are real numbers.  We call the collection of numbers of this form the &lt;em&gt;quaternions&lt;/em&gt;, which we denote by &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{H}\)&lt;/span&gt;.  Here &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{H}\)&lt;/span&gt; stands for Hamilton, as in &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Rowan_Hamilton"&gt;William Rowan Hamilton&lt;/a&gt;, the Irish mathematician who first constructed the quaternions. (The perhaps more natural &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{Q}\)&lt;/span&gt; is already taken, as this is used to denote the rational numbers.) We can see that the quaternions extend the complex numbers &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{C}\)&lt;/span&gt;, since we can consider a complex number &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(a+bi\)&lt;/span&gt; as a quaternion &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(a + bi + 0j + 0k\)&lt;/span&gt; where the &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(j, k\)&lt;/span&gt; part of the quaternion are simply 0.  The quaternions are evidently a four-dimensional number system, as a single quaternion actually represents a set of four real numbers.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the form &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(q = a + bi + cj + dk\)&lt;/span&gt; it is easy to see how to add quaternions.  We have, for two quaternions &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(q_0, q_1\)&lt;/span&gt;, that
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
q_0 + q_1 = (a_0 + b_0i + c_0j + d_0k) + (a_1 + b_1i + c_1j + d_1 k) = (a_0 + a_1) + (b_0 + b_1)i + (c_0 + c_1)j + (d_0 + d_1)k,
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
that is, we can add quaternions simply by "adding like terms."  Subtraction of quaternions is defined similarly.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more difficult property to define is multiplication.  As in the case of the complex numbers, the crucial point is to understand how to define multiplication amongst the "new" numbers &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(i, j, k\)&lt;/span&gt;.  The appropriate multiplication rules are what Hamilton discovered when he constructed the quaternions.  Apparently he was walking with his wife one day along a canal in Dublin when he suddenly realized the correct multiplication rule, and he was so excited that he immediately carved the formula into a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History_of_quaternions#Hamilton's_discovery"&gt;bridge along the canal&lt;/a&gt;:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
i^2 = j^2 = k^2 = ijk = -1
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here we use juxtaposition to denote multiplication, that is, &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(ij\)&lt;/span&gt; means the same thing as &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(i \times j\)&lt;/span&gt;. We'll sometimes also denote multiplication with a small dot, e.g., &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(i \cdot j\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above multiplication rule is more commonly written in the equivalent form
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
i^2 = j^2 = k^2 = -1 \text{ and } ij = k = -ji.
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This latter form makes the most important feature of quaternion multiplication more obvious: it is &lt;em&gt;not commutative&lt;/em&gt;.  We say an operation is commutative if the order of the operands does not matter.  For example, addition of real numbers is commutative because &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(a + b = b + a\)&lt;/span&gt; for all real numbers.  Likewise the multiplication of real numbers is commutative, as are both addition and multiplication of complex numbers. Subtraction of real numbers is not commutative, since in general &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(a - b \neq b - a\)&lt;/span&gt;.  To say that quaternionic multiplication is not commutative is to say that if &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(p, q\)&lt;/span&gt; are quaternions, then in general we have that &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(p q \neq q p\)&lt;/span&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using the above rules for multiplying the elements &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(i, j, k\)&lt;/span&gt;, we can define the product of any two quaternions in a way that's very similar to the method for the complex numbers, by treating &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(i, j, k\)&lt;/span&gt; as variables but simplifying any multiplication between these numbers using the multiplication rules above.  After a simple but somewhat tedious computation, we arrive at the following general formula for multiplication of any two quaternions:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{align*}
q_0 q_1 &amp;amp;= (a_0 + b_0i + c_0j + d_0k) \cdot (a_1 + b_1i + c_1j + d_1k) \\
&amp;amp;= (a_0 a_1 - b_0 b_1 -c_0 c_1 - d_0 d_1)+ (a_1 b_0 + a_0 b_1 - c_1 d_0 + c_0 d_1) i \\
 &amp;amp;\hspace{.25in}+ (a_1 c_0 + a_0 c_1 + b_1 d_0 - b_0 d_1)j + (-b_1 c_0 + b_0 c_1 + a_1 d_0 + a_0 d_1)k
\end{align*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we'd like to consider quaternionic division as well.  Similar to the complex case, we will actually define an inverse operation, and again this will be based on a conjugation operation.  If &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(q = a + bi + cj +dk\)&lt;/span&gt; is a quaternion, then we will call &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(a\)&lt;/span&gt; the &lt;em&gt;real part&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(bi + cj + dk\)&lt;/span&gt; the &lt;em&gt;imaginary part&lt;/em&gt;, and once again the complex conjugation operation will consist of switching the sign of the imaginary part, that is
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
\overline{q} = a - bi - cj - dk
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Just as in the case of complex numbers, we can observe that &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(|q|^2 = q \overline{q} = a^2 + b^2 + c^2 +d^2\)&lt;/span&gt; is a real number (i.e., has no imaginary part), and that the inverse of a quaternion will be given by
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
q^{-1} = \frac{1}{|q|^2}\overline{q} = \frac{a}{a^2+b^2+c^2+d^2} + \frac{-b}{a^2+b^2+c^2+d^2}i + \frac{-c}{a^2+b^2+c^2+d^2}j + \frac{-d}{a^2+b^2+c^2+d^2}k
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fractions of quaternions, are actually not exactly defined since multiplication is not commutative.  If we'd like to take the quaternionic fraction &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\frac{q}{p}\)&lt;/span&gt;, then, using the understanding that "division" means the same thing as "multiplying by the inverse", the value of the division should be the same as the number obtained by multiplying &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(q\)&lt;/span&gt; by &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(p^{-1}\)&lt;/span&gt;.  However there are two ways to do this multiplication, either &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(p^{-1}q\)&lt;/span&gt; or &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(qp^{-1}\)&lt;/span&gt;, that will in general not be the same since quaternionic multiplication is not commutative.  Therefore we will never write quaternions as fractions, and instead only consider multiplication by the inverse so that the order of the operands is clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a note on terminology, in the last post we said that the real numbers and the complex numbers are both examples of &lt;em&gt;fields&lt;/em&gt; since they possess addition, subtraction, multiplication, and division operations. One of the additional requirements of a field that went unmentioned in that post is that the multiplication in a field should be commutative. The quaternions are therefore not a field.  Instead, the quaternions are known as a "division algebra." The term "skew field" is also used in older books, but is less common today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;And Beyond&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the previous post, we saw that we could extend the one-dimensional real number system using the two-dimensional complex numbers.  In this post, we extended the complex numbers by the four-dimensional quaternions. Each time, we've managed to extend the number system by doubling the dimension. Could we keep going? Are there further number systems with dimension 8, 16, 32, and so on?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer is yes, although the number systems that arise in this way are not generally as useful.  Each extension process we have discussed so far is an example of a general construction called the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cayley–Dickson_construction"&gt;Cayley-Dickson construction&lt;/a&gt;.  This is a procedure that takes one of the number systems we have been discussing and produces a new number system of twice the dimension.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new number systems constructed by this process, though, always lose some of the desirable algebraic properties of the starting point.  For example, in moving from &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{R}\)&lt;/span&gt; to &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{C}\)&lt;/span&gt;, we lose the property that the real numbers are ordered. Similarly, we lose the commutativity of multiplication when we extend from &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{C}\)&lt;/span&gt; to &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{H}\)&lt;/span&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We could apply the Cayley-Dickson construction again to the quaternions to produce an 8-dimensional number system called the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Octonion"&gt;octonions&lt;/a&gt;. In constructing these numbers, we lose the property of &lt;em&gt;associativity&lt;/em&gt; of multiplication, which is the property that the result of multiplication is independent of the grouping.  That is, given three numbers &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(a, b, c\)&lt;/span&gt;, we could form the product of these numbers in two different ways (fixing the order), as either &lt;span class="math"&gt;\((ab)c\)&lt;/span&gt; or as &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(a(bc)\)&lt;/span&gt;. The reals, complexes, and quaternions are all associative, in that this grouping does not matter, e.g.,
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
(2 \cdot 3) \cdot 4 = 6 \cdot 4 = 24 = 2 \cdot 12 = 2 \cdot (3 \cdot 4)
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is no longer the case for the octonions. Even so, the octonions are still useful in mathematics and also in some physics applications, although we won't discuss the octonions any further.  One can continue past the octonions as well (the next number system is called the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sedenion"&gt;sedenions&lt;/a&gt;) but these further number systems are not commonly studied by mathematicians - after repeating the Cayley-Dickson construction so many times they have lost enough algebraic properties that they are no longer as useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Why the Quaternions?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the above we've seen what the quaternions are from an axiomatic perspective. We've defined a quaternion as a collection of 4 real numbers, and given ways to add, subtract, multiply, and divide quaternions. This is interesting, but it may make the quaternions seem like an odd curiosity. Have we just found a set of weird rules for manipulating quadruplets of numbers, or do the quaternions actually amount to something?.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The complex numbers have something of this flavor, as a weird system for manipulating pairs of numbers. But we saw in the previous post that they actually solve an important problem: they're an algebraically closed extension of the real numbers. What problems were the quaternions meant to solve? Why did Hamilton think they were important enough to vandalize a bridge when he discovered them? In our  next few posts, we'll answer that question, when we see that the quaternions are intimately related with the geometry of rotations in three dimensions.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;if (!document.getElementById('mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#')) {
    var align = "center",
        indent = "0em",
        linebreak = "false";

    if (false) {
        align = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "left" : align;
        indent = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "0em" : indent;
        linebreak = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? 'true' : linebreak;
    }

    var mathjaxscript = document.createElement('script');
    mathjaxscript.id = 'mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#';
    mathjaxscript.type = 'text/javascript';
    mathjaxscript.src = 'https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.0/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML';
    mathjaxscript[(window.opera ? "innerHTML" : "text")] =
        "MathJax.Hub.Config({" +
        "    config: ['MMLorHTML.js']," +
        "    TeX: { extensions: ['AMSmath.js','AMSsymbols.js','noErrors.js','noUndefined.js'], equationNumbers: { autoNumber: 'AMS' } }," +
        "    jax: ['input/TeX','input/MathML','output/HTML-CSS']," +
        "    extensions: ['tex2jax.js','mml2jax.js','MathMenu.js','MathZoom.js']," +
        "    displayAlign: '"+ align +"'," +
        "    displayIndent: '"+ indent +"'," +
        "    showMathMenu: true," +
        "    messageStyle: 'normal'," +
        "    tex2jax: { " +
        "        inlineMath: [ ['\\\\(','\\\\)'] ], " +
        "        displayMath: [ ['$$','$$'] ]," +
        "        processEscapes: true," +
        "        preview: 'TeX'," +
        "    }, " +
        "    'HTML-CSS': { " +
        "        styles: { '.MathJax_Display, .MathJax .mo, .MathJax .mi, .MathJax .mn': {color: 'inherit ! important'} }," +
        "        linebreaks: { automatic: "+ linebreak +", width: '90% container' }," +
        "    }, " +
        "}); " +
        "if ('default' !== 'default') {" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('HTML-CSS Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax['HTML-CSS'].FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('SVG Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax.SVG.FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
        "}";
    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(mathjaxscript);
}
&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="thesis"></category><category term="quaternions"></category></entry><entry><title>On the Way to the Quaternions: Real and Complex Numbers</title><link href="http://www.josephthurman.com/quaternions1.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-02-22T10:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-02-22T10:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Joseph Thurman</name></author><id>tag:www.josephthurman.com,2018-02-22:/quaternions1.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href="http://www.josephthurman.com/first-series-explaining-my-thesis.html"&gt;introductory post&lt;/a&gt; to this series of posts explaining my thesis, we first heard about "quaternion-K&amp;auml;hler manifolds," a type of geometric object with special curvature properties.  These special geometric properties are related to the algebraic properties of the &lt;em&gt;quaternions&lt;/em&gt;, a 4-dimensional number system that generalizes the somewhat more familiar …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href="http://www.josephthurman.com/first-series-explaining-my-thesis.html"&gt;introductory post&lt;/a&gt; to this series of posts explaining my thesis, we first heard about "quaternion-K&amp;auml;hler manifolds," a type of geometric object with special curvature properties.  These special geometric properties are related to the algebraic properties of the &lt;em&gt;quaternions&lt;/em&gt;, a 4-dimensional number system that generalizes the somewhat more familiar real and complex number systems. In this post, we'll lay the groundwork for defining the quaternions by discussing some properties of the real and complex numbers. A good understanding of these two number systems, and especially of the complex numbers, will be necessary to understand the more complicated quaternions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Real Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real number system, often denote in mathematics by the symbol &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{R}\)&lt;/span&gt;, is the number system associated to the concept of the "number line" that is often taught in schools.  That is, if one considers a straight, infinitely long line, then every point on that line can be associated to a number.  We can choose a center point for the line, which we associate to the number 0, and then could repeatedly move to the right by a fixed distance to mark the points associated to 1, 2, 3, etc., and similarly to the left for the points -1, -2, -3, etc.  All other points on this line also represent numbers - the point exactly halfway between -1 and -2 is the point -3/2, while the number &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\pi = 3.14159\ldots\)&lt;/span&gt; is associated to a point that's a little to the right of 3, and so on.  All real numbers can be written as decimals (although those decimals might repeat infinitely, as in &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(1/3 = 0.3333333\ldots\)&lt;/span&gt;, or might even go one forever without any discernible pattern, as in &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\pi\)&lt;/span&gt;), and using these decimal expressions we have methods for adding, subtracting, multiplying and dividing real numbers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The number line" src="http://www.josephthurman.com/numberline.png"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The real number line&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the idea of the real number line is fairly intuitive, the formal mathematical definition of the real numbers is rather complicated, and a great deal of mathematical energy was expended to define and understand the real numbers.  This technical work is in one sense extremely important to my own thesis work, in that it is the foundation for all of calculus and therefore for all of my work.  On the other hand, Newton and Leibniz invented calculus without a mathematically rigorous definition of the real number system, and if they didn't need all of the gory technical details, then we won't spend too much time worrying about them either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that said, we will say a few important facts about the real numbers.  First, the real numbers are a &lt;em&gt;field&lt;/em&gt;, the mathematical word for set equipped with operations that behave like addition, subtraction, multiplication, and division. The abstract definition of a field was essentially made to generalize the structure of the real numbers.  The real number field has two extra properties, though, that make it special.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, it is &lt;em&gt;ordered&lt;/em&gt;, that is, for any two numbers &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(x, y\)&lt;/span&gt; we can always say that either &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(x \leq y\)&lt;/span&gt; or &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(y \leq x\)&lt;/span&gt; (or both if we actually have &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(x = y\)&lt;/span&gt;) and that this order satisfies some extra properties to make it consistent with the addition and multiplication operations. (One of these is that if &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(x \geq 0\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(y \geq 0\)&lt;/span&gt;, then we also have that the product &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(xy \geq 0\)&lt;/span&gt;.)  Not every field is ordered. For example, since the complex numbers discussed below are two dimensional, they do not admit an order that's compatible with the field structure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, the real numbers are &lt;em&gt;Dedekind-complete&lt;/em&gt; with respect to this order. This property is also known as the "least upper bound property." It says that, given any non-empty collection of real numbers that has some upper bound (a number &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(M\)&lt;/span&gt; such that if &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(x\)&lt;/span&gt; is a number in the collection, &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(x \leq M\)&lt;/span&gt;), then that collection has a &lt;em&gt;smallest&lt;/em&gt; upper bound.  This is also not true for every field. In particular, the &lt;em&gt;rational&lt;/em&gt; numbers do not have this property.  The rational numbers are the set of numbers that can be expressed as a ratio of two integers (for example, &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(2\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(-5/4\)&lt;/span&gt; are rational, while &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\pi\)&lt;/span&gt; is not). The rational numbers are also a field, since one can add, subtract, multiply, and divide fractions (and the result is always a fraction), and are in fact an ordered field as well.  They are not, however, Dedekind-complete. To see why, consider the set of all rational numbers less than &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\sqrt{2}\)&lt;/span&gt;. This set is bounded, and it's not hard to see that the least upper bound of this set is &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\sqrt{2}\)&lt;/span&gt;. But &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\sqrt{2}\)&lt;/span&gt; is irrational, so the set of rational numbers does not have the least upper bound property since the least upper bound &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\sqrt{2}\)&lt;/span&gt; is not itself a rational number.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One can show with a fair amount of work that these two properties uniquely determine the real numbers, that is, there is exactly one ordered, Dedekind-complete field. Still, making a formal mathematical construction of a field that satisfies these two properties is not easy, and the interested reader can search the internet for more information on either &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dedekind_cut"&gt;Dedekind cuts&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Construction_of_the_real_numbers#Construction_from_Cauchy_sequences"&gt;Cauchy sequences&lt;/a&gt;. For the future, we'll only need the intuitive understanding of the real numbers as the points along the number line, but it's good to point out the difficulties in defining the real number line as an example of the way that seemingly intuitive concepts can hide a great deal of mathematical complexity.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Complex Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One drawback of the real numbers is that they are not &lt;em&gt;algebraically closed&lt;/em&gt;. This means that not every real polynomial has real roots.  A &lt;em&gt;real polynomial&lt;/em&gt; is an expression with the form
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
p(x) = a_n x^n + a_{n-1} x^{n-1} + \cdots + a_2 x^2 + a_1 x + a_0
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
where the coefficients &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(a_n, \ldots, a_0\)&lt;/span&gt; are real numbers and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(x\)&lt;/span&gt; is a variable.  A &lt;em&gt;root&lt;/em&gt; of a polynomial is a value for &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(x\)&lt;/span&gt; that makes &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(p(x) = 0\)&lt;/span&gt;.  For example, &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(1\)&lt;/span&gt; is a root of the polynomial &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(q(x) = x^2 - 1\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But we can find polynomials with real-number coefficients that do not have any real-number roots, such as
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
p(x) = x^2 + 1
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For any real number &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(x\)&lt;/span&gt;, the square &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(x^2 \geq 0\)&lt;/span&gt;, and so &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(x^2 + 1 &amp;gt; 0\)&lt;/span&gt; and there can be no real roots.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's somewhat inconvenient to have equations involving only real numbers that are still impossible to solve.  To fix this problem, we can define a new number &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(i\)&lt;/span&gt;, called the &lt;em&gt;imaginary unit&lt;/em&gt;, to be a number such that &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(i^2 = -1\)&lt;/span&gt; so that &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(i\)&lt;/span&gt; is a root of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(p(x)\)&lt;/span&gt; above. This leads to the definition of the &lt;em&gt;complex numbers&lt;/em&gt;. A complex number &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z\)&lt;/span&gt; consists of a pair of real numbers &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(a, b\)&lt;/span&gt;, which we call the &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;imaginary&lt;/em&gt; parts, respectively, and we write &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z = a + bi\)&lt;/span&gt;. The set of all complex numbers is denoted by &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{C}\)&lt;/span&gt;.  Note that we can consider the real numbers &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{R}\)&lt;/span&gt; as a subset of the complex numbers: if &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(a\)&lt;/span&gt; is a real number, we can consider it as the complex number &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(a + 0 i\)&lt;/span&gt;, that is, a complex number with no imaginary part. This is a two dimensional number system, since a number in &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{C}\)&lt;/span&gt; actually consists of a &lt;em&gt;pair&lt;/em&gt; of real numbers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The choice of the word "imaginary" to describe these numbers is unfortunate, since it implies that these numbers aren't actually numbers and are just strange mathematical objects someone dreamed up. (This terminology was coined by Ren&amp;eacute; Descartes, of "I think therefore I am" fame, in order to denigrate the complex numbers in exactly this way.) And some would say this criticism makes sense. After all, these numbers are defined so that the equation &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(X^2 + 1 = 0\)&lt;/span&gt; can have a solution, and some might say that this equation obviously has no solutions and it's silly to ask for one.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such objections are based on opinion, though, which doesn't really count for much in formal mathematics.  Worse, the same kind of argument could be used to ignore any number of mathematical topics.  Consider negative numbers: they were introduced to be able to solve equations like, say, &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(X + 5 = 2\)&lt;/span&gt;. But this equation is ridiculous and obviously shouldn't have a solution - after all, if you started with &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(X\)&lt;/span&gt; apples and someone gave you five apples, how could you end with only 2?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arguments about whether or not certain numbers are "real" in a philosophical sense can get surprisingly heated.  Consider for example the irrational numbers, that is, real numbers that are not rational numbers. Actually, if you happen to follow a Pythagorean philosophy, it's probably safer not to. The Pythagorean theorem is named after Pythagoras, an ancient Greek philosopher who also lead something like a cult that was based around mathematical principles.  His and his followers' theology was heavily influenced by music and harmony, where many important concepts like scales and consonance are related to having only whole-number ratios of numbers.  They were so invested in the divine order of rational numbers that it's sometimes said that they denied the existence of irrational numbers, going so far as to &lt;a href="https://io9.gizmodo.com/did-pythagoras-really-murder-a-guy-1460668208"&gt;murder one of their own members&lt;/a&gt; for proving that &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\sqrt{2}\)&lt;/span&gt; is irrational. (The story of the murder probably isn't actually true, partly because there is some disagreement about exactly which irrational number was the cause for the murder. The story linked above says it's the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Golden_ratio"&gt;golden ratio&lt;/a&gt;, but the version with &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\sqrt{2}\)&lt;/span&gt; is also common.) Somewhat ironically, the Pythagoreans would have thought about &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\sqrt{2}\)&lt;/span&gt; because, if a perfect square has a side length of 1, then the length of the diagonal will be &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\sqrt{2}\)&lt;/span&gt;, a fact that one can prove using the Pythagorean theorem.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus if you think it makes sense to talk about negative numbers, or irrational numbers, then you should think it makes perfectly good sense to talk about imaginary numbers and complex numbers as well.  If nothing else, we'll see in a later post that complex numbers can and do have a real physical significance, even if it's less obvious than applications of other number systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Operations with Complex Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With any concerns about the ontological status of the complex numbers brushed aside, we can now define operations with complex numbers. We will define addition, subtraction, multiplication, and division rules for complex numbers so that &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\mathbb{C}\)&lt;/span&gt; is also a field.  Addition and subtraction are defined in a fairly straightforward way, essentially by considering &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(i\)&lt;/span&gt; as a variable and combining like terms.  That is, if &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z = a + bi\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(w = c + di\)&lt;/span&gt; are complex numbers, then
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
z \pm w = (a + bi) \pm (c + di) = (a \pm c) + (b \pm d)i
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We just add (or subtract) the real parts and the imaginary parts separately.  Multiplication is defined by again treating &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(i\)&lt;/span&gt; as a variable, but also making the simplification that &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(i^2 = -1\)&lt;/span&gt; wherever possible. Therefore we have
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{align*}
z \times w &amp;amp;= (a+bi) \times (c+di) \\
  &amp;amp;= ac + adi + bci + bdi^2 \\
  &amp;amp;= ac + adi + bci - bd \\
  &amp;amp;= (ac - bd) + (ad + bc)i
\end{align*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We'll generally drop the multiplication sign, and denote multiplication just by juxtaposition, i.e., &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(zw\)&lt;/span&gt; means the same as &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z \times w\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To define division of complex numbers, we can consider one extra operation on complex numbers, called &lt;em&gt;complex conjugation&lt;/em&gt;.  Given a complex number &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z = a + bi\)&lt;/span&gt;, then its complex conjugate, denoted by &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\overline{z}\)&lt;/span&gt;, is the complex number &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\overline{z} = a - bi\)&lt;/span&gt;, that is, we switch the sign on the imaginary part of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z\)&lt;/span&gt;.  Complex conjugation is special because the product of a complex number and its complex conjugate is always a real number:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{align*}
z \overline{z} &amp;amp;= (a+bi)(a-bi) \\
  &amp;amp;= a^2 - abi + abi - b^2 i^2 \\
  &amp;amp;= a^2 + b^2
\end{align*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The number &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\sqrt{z \overline{z}} = \sqrt{a^2 + b^2}\)&lt;/span&gt; is also called the &lt;em&gt;norm&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;modulus&lt;/em&gt; of &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z\)&lt;/span&gt;, and will be discussed more in a later post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we have defined complex conjugation, we can write the rule for division of complex numbers. It's actually easier to define a different operation, called the &lt;em&gt;inverse&lt;/em&gt; of a complex number.  Given a nonzero complex number &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z\)&lt;/span&gt;, we will define the inverse to be the complex number denoted by &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z^{-1}\)&lt;/span&gt; with the property that &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(zz^{-1} = 1\)&lt;/span&gt;. (Zero has no inverse, since &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(0\)&lt;/span&gt; times any complex number can never be 1. This is ok because division by 0 is not defined anyway). Defining an inverse is the same as defining division, since division is just the operation that  undoes multiplication.  That is, if we have the product &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(wz\)&lt;/span&gt; and want to undo the multiplication by &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z\)&lt;/span&gt;, one way to do so would be to "divide by &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z\)&lt;/span&gt;" to be left with just &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(w\)&lt;/span&gt;.  Since we could also take &lt;span class="math"&gt;\((wz)z^{-1} = w (z z^{-1}) = w (1) = w\)&lt;/span&gt;, we define "division by &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z\)&lt;/span&gt;" to be the same as "multiplication by the inverse &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(z^{-1}\)&lt;/span&gt;".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what is the inverse?  Using the conjugation operator, we can define
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
z^{-1} = \frac{1}{|z|^2} \overline{z} = \frac{a}{a^2+b^2} - \frac{b}{a^2 + b^2}i
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To check that this is correct, observe that
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{align*}
zz^{-1} &amp;amp;= (a+bi)\left( \frac{a}{a^2+b^2} - \frac{b}{a^2 + b^2} i \right) \\
  &amp;amp;= \frac{a^2}{a^2 + b^2} - \frac{ab}{a^2 + b^2} i + \frac{ab}{a^2 + b^2} i - \frac{b^2}{a^2+b^2}i^2 \\
  &amp;amp;= \frac{a^2}{a^2 + b^2} + \frac{b^2}{a^2+b^2} = \frac{a^2+b^2}{a^2 + b^2} = 1
\end{align*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we have that the complex numbers are a field, but what are they good for? Returning to the motivation for the construction of the complex numbers in the previous section, one can show that the complex numbers are algebraically closed. That is, any (nonconstant) polynomial with &lt;em&gt;complex&lt;/em&gt; coefficients will always have a complex root.  Since real numbers are themselves a subset of the complex numbers, this means that any polynomial equation with real coefficients can always be solved using complex numbers.  The fact that the complex numbers are algebraically closed is known as the "Fundamental Theorem of Algebra."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This leads to one of the main situations in which a non-mathematician might have encountered complex numbers in school.  Many people learn the quadratic formula, which, given a quadratic equation of the form
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
ax^2 + bx + c = 0,
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
says that the solutions of this equation are given by the pair of values
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="math"&gt;\begin{equation*}
x = \frac{-b \pm \sqrt{b^2 - 4ac}}{2a}
\end{equation*}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The first time one encounters this formula, they learn that the number &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(b^2 - 4ac\)&lt;/span&gt; is called the &lt;em&gt;discriminant&lt;/em&gt;, and that the quadratic equation has no solution if this value is negative, since one cannot take the square root of a negative number.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, one can't take the square root of a negative number and obtain a real number, but we've seen that the complex numbers are specifically constructed so that we can take square roots of negative numbers. The imaginary unit &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(i\)&lt;/span&gt; is after all defined to be &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\sqrt{-1}\)&lt;/span&gt;.  By expanding our number system and considering complex numbers, we can therefore see from this formula that all quadratic equations can be solved - we just have to use complex numbers for the solution in the case that the discriminant is negative. The Fundamental Theorem of Algebra, moreover, says that roots can be found for any polynomial, if one allows for complex number solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Next Time - The Quaternions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this understanding of the real and complex number system, we're ready to actually define the quaternions in the next post.  We'll see that they are a four-dimensional extension of the complex numbers that has many of the same properties of the complex numbers, but with a few major differences as well.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;if (!document.getElementById('mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#')) {
    var align = "center",
        indent = "0em",
        linebreak = "false";

    if (false) {
        align = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "left" : align;
        indent = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "0em" : indent;
        linebreak = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? 'true' : linebreak;
    }

    var mathjaxscript = document.createElement('script');
    mathjaxscript.id = 'mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#';
    mathjaxscript.type = 'text/javascript';
    mathjaxscript.src = 'https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.0/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML';
    mathjaxscript[(window.opera ? "innerHTML" : "text")] =
        "MathJax.Hub.Config({" +
        "    config: ['MMLorHTML.js']," +
        "    TeX: { extensions: ['AMSmath.js','AMSsymbols.js','noErrors.js','noUndefined.js'], equationNumbers: { autoNumber: 'AMS' } }," +
        "    jax: ['input/TeX','input/MathML','output/HTML-CSS']," +
        "    extensions: ['tex2jax.js','mml2jax.js','MathMenu.js','MathZoom.js']," +
        "    displayAlign: '"+ align +"'," +
        "    displayIndent: '"+ indent +"'," +
        "    showMathMenu: true," +
        "    messageStyle: 'normal'," +
        "    tex2jax: { " +
        "        inlineMath: [ ['\\\\(','\\\\)'] ], " +
        "        displayMath: [ ['$$','$$'] ]," +
        "        processEscapes: true," +
        "        preview: 'TeX'," +
        "    }, " +
        "    'HTML-CSS': { " +
        "        styles: { '.MathJax_Display, .MathJax .mo, .MathJax .mi, .MathJax .mn': {color: 'inherit ! important'} }," +
        "        linebreaks: { automatic: "+ linebreak +", width: '90% container' }," +
        "    }, " +
        "}); " +
        "if ('default' !== 'default') {" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('HTML-CSS Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax['HTML-CSS'].FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('SVG Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax.SVG.FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
        "}";
    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(mathjaxscript);
}
&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="thesis"></category><category term="quaternions"></category><category term="complex numbers"></category></entry><entry><title>First Series - Explaining my Thesis</title><link href="http://www.josephthurman.com/first-series-explaining-my-thesis.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-02-08T17:08:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-02-08T17:08:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Joseph Thurman</name></author><id>tag:www.josephthurman.com,2018-02-08:/first-series-explaining-my-thesis.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;When you're a mathematics PhD student, your work is likely to be totally inscrutable to just about anyone you meet, even many fellow mathematicians. This is probably true for advanced research work in nearly any field, but I think the problem is especially bad in pure mathematics, largely for two …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When you're a mathematics PhD student, your work is likely to be totally inscrutable to just about anyone you meet, even many fellow mathematicians. This is probably true for advanced research work in nearly any field, but I think the problem is especially bad in pure mathematics, largely for two reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first is that the the objects of study in mathematics are often unfamiliar and, to an outsider at least, hopelessly abstract. As a comparison, one of my brothers is also an academic, working on a PhD in biology and studying evolution in butterflies. The real details of his work are beyond me, but I learned the basics of evolution in high school, and I definitely know what a butterfly is, so he can tell me something about his work and I at least know what he's talking about. In contrast, my academic research involves various constructions related to quaternion-K&amp;auml;hler manifolds, and if you know what that means, congratulations to you on finishing your math PhD!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second problem is that the way that mathematicians think about math, especially the way they do research, is very different from the way that many people learn about mathematics in school. If you stopped learning math in high school or in a first-year calculus course in college, you probably think of math as a collection of formulas to be applied to solving problems on a worksheet. But before those formulas can be used to solve problems, someone has to come up with them, and understand why they work. Even more crucially, someone has to build the logical framework that gives the formulas and their applications context. This is what mathematicians actually do -- they define different abstract logical systems and try to understand their properties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a simple example, consider arithmetic, that is, addition, subtraction, multiplication, and division.  Middle school students learn algorithms like long division to compute these operations, and then spend weeks doing worksheets where they divide various numbers over and over.  This is important to be able to do, but a mathematician would want to ask more questions: for example, what is a number, exactly, and what does it mean to multiply two numbers? A mathematician might notice that multiplication is an operation that takes in two objects from the collection of numbers and produces a third number, subject to various rules - for example, commutativity (that &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(a \times b = b \times a\)&lt;/span&gt;) and distribution over addition (that &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(a \times (b + c) = a \times b + a \times c\)&lt;/span&gt;). They might then try to consider other collections of objects and construct multiplication-like rules for those collections. In particular, the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quaternion"&gt;quaternions&lt;/a&gt;, which feature prominently in my thesis, are a number system constructed by the mathematician William Rowan Hamilton in the process of trying to find a way to "multiply" triples of numbers. Thinking about these abstract structures and trying to deduce their properties is, to a mathematician at least, far more interesting that doing worksheet after worksheet of long division problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is the first in a series that will ultimately attempt to explain the results of my thesis to a general audience (or at least my family, who might be the only people who ever read this). I hope not only to explain the esoteric and abstract objects that I spend most of my time thinking about, but also to demonstrate the way that mathematicians think about math.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before embarking on that journey, though, I'll give the shortest summary of my work that I can. It's common advice for academics of all types to always have an "elevator pitch" explanation of their research that they could give to anyone in under two minutes. Mine goes something like this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Two-Minute Summary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I work in differential geometry, an area of mathematics that studies how to measure distances in spaces, and how spaces can themselves curve and bend. One of the most familiar geometric spaces is a flat, 2-dimensional, infinite plane - basically like a sheet of paper extended out as large as conceivably possible. High school geometry is really the study of this one space - learning about angles, distances, shapes, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are other spaces that one can study, though, with different geometries. As an example, consider the surface of the earth, which (if we imagine that the earth is perfectly smooth) has the geometry of a "round 2-sphere." It is also a two-dimensional geometry, in that you can specify a location on the surface of the earth using two numbers, latitude and longitude, and all the same concepts of geometry still apply - you can still talk about distances between points, angles, shapes on this surface, etc. It is very different from the flat geometry, though. For example, you could (in principle) continually walk in a fixed direction, and in doing so walk around the whole world and end up back at your starting point, which is definitely not possible on the flat plane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main difference between these two geometries is a property called curvature. In two dimensions, there is a number that one can assign to every point of a space that describes how curved that space is at that point. For the flat piece of paper, that number is 0 for every point. For the sphere, that number is positive at every point. In fact, if &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(R\)&lt;/span&gt; is the radius of the sphere, then the curvature is given by &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(1/R^2\)&lt;/span&gt;. For example, the curvature of the earth, which has a large radius, would be a small, but positive number. This agrees with our perception that the earth &lt;em&gt;seems&lt;/em&gt; flat when you walk around, and that you'd have to walk a long way to notice it curving. If you could walk around on the surface of a smaller sphere, like a basketball, you'd definitely notice the curvature. There are also two dimensional spaces of &lt;em&gt;negative&lt;/em&gt; curvature. "Negative" curvature just means that the surface curves in opposite directions. An example is the surface of a horse saddle -- the surface curves down to the ground on the left and right (where your legs go), but curves up to the sky in front and behind. A sphere always curves in the same direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Illustration of Curvature Types" src="http://www.josephthurman.com/3spaces.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Examples of 2-dimensional surfaces with positive, zero, and negative curvature&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These concepts are easy to visualize for two-dimensional surfaces sitting in three-dimensional space (as illustrated above), but most geometry research is concerned with higher dimensions, where things are much more complicated. According to general relativity, for example, the universe is a four-dimensional geometric object, with the three familiar spatial dimensions and an extra time dimension, and the way that this "spacetime" curves determines the gravitational field. The concept of curvature is also more complicated in higher dimensions,  where one needs many numbers to describe the curvature of the space in the many possible different directions, instead of the single number necessary in two dimensions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As stated above, I study "quaternion-K&amp;auml;hler manifolds." These are higher-dimensional geometries, occurring in dimensions divisible by 4 (i.e., 4, 8, 12, ...) that have a very particular type of curvature, that makes them interesting in various mathematical applications and in theoretical physics.  My work on these spaces is an attempt to understand both how many different types of quaternion-K&amp;auml;hler manifolds exist and how these spaces can be used to construct other geometries with interesting curvature properties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;if (!document.getElementById('mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#')) {
    var align = "center",
        indent = "0em",
        linebreak = "false";

    if (false) {
        align = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "left" : align;
        indent = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "0em" : indent;
        linebreak = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? 'true' : linebreak;
    }

    var mathjaxscript = document.createElement('script');
    mathjaxscript.id = 'mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#';
    mathjaxscript.type = 'text/javascript';
    mathjaxscript.src = 'https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.0/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML';
    mathjaxscript[(window.opera ? "innerHTML" : "text")] =
        "MathJax.Hub.Config({" +
        "    config: ['MMLorHTML.js']," +
        "    TeX: { extensions: ['AMSmath.js','AMSsymbols.js','noErrors.js','noUndefined.js'], equationNumbers: { autoNumber: 'AMS' } }," +
        "    jax: ['input/TeX','input/MathML','output/HTML-CSS']," +
        "    extensions: ['tex2jax.js','mml2jax.js','MathMenu.js','MathZoom.js']," +
        "    displayAlign: '"+ align +"'," +
        "    displayIndent: '"+ indent +"'," +
        "    showMathMenu: true," +
        "    messageStyle: 'normal'," +
        "    tex2jax: { " +
        "        inlineMath: [ ['\\\\(','\\\\)'] ], " +
        "        displayMath: [ ['$$','$$'] ]," +
        "        processEscapes: true," +
        "        preview: 'TeX'," +
        "    }, " +
        "    'HTML-CSS': { " +
        "        styles: { '.MathJax_Display, .MathJax .mo, .MathJax .mi, .MathJax .mn': {color: 'inherit ! important'} }," +
        "        linebreaks: { automatic: "+ linebreak +", width: '90% container' }," +
        "    }, " +
        "}); " +
        "if ('default' !== 'default') {" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('HTML-CSS Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax['HTML-CSS'].FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('SVG Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax.SVG.FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
        "}";
    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(mathjaxscript);
}
&lt;/script&gt;</content></entry></feed>